<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nyne songs collected out of the Holy Scriptures of Old and New Testament, drawne foorth of the pure fountaines of Hebreuu and Greeke ; translated, paraphrased in prose, summed, analysed, notted vpon, grounds for vse and doctrine observed in every one of them, and finally paraphrased in English meeter, by Mr. William Moray ...</title>
            <author>Morray, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07789</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1306</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22108112</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22108112</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25087</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07789)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25087)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1732:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nyne songs collected out of the Holy Scriptures of Old and New Testament, drawne foorth of the pure fountaines of Hebreuu and Greeke ; translated, paraphrased in prose, summed, analysed, notted vpon, grounds for vse and doctrine observed in every one of them, and finally paraphrased in English meeter, by Mr. William Moray ...</title>
                  <author>Morray, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 100 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[J. Wreittoun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint cropped; publisher and date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Edinburgh. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  English. --  Selections --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  Selections --  Paraphrases, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25087:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25087:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NYNE SONGS</p>
            <p>Collected out of the holy SCRIPTURES of Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament: drawne foorth of the pure fountaines of HEBREVV and GREEKE.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated, Paraphraſed in proſe, Summed, Analyſed, notted vpon, grounds for vſe and doctrine obſerved in every one of them, and finally para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſed in Engliſh meeter.</p>
            <p>By M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. WILLIAM MORAY, Miniſter of GODS word in Crail.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Colloſſ. 1.3. Verſe 16.</bibl> Let the word of CHRIST dwell in you plenteouſly in all wiſdome, teaching and admoniſhing one another, in Pſalmes and Hymnes, and ſpirituall ſongs, ſinging with ſpirituall grace in your hearts to the LORD.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iam. 5.13.</bibl> Is any among you afflicted? let him pray. Is any merrie? le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him ſing Pſalmes.</q>
            <p>EDINBVRGH, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25087:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25087:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE VICOVNT OF STORMONT, LORD OF SCONE, and of <hi>BAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WHIDDER, Stewart of</hi> FYFE, &amp;c. One of the <hi>Kings moſt excellent</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties priuie counſellers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I looke backe vpon the courſe of your L. life, whom I haue knowne about fourtie eight yeares agoe: I cannot but wonder of the goodneſſe and gratious providence of GOD towards your L. For ſo ſoone as your L. went to the Court of that Prince of worthy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie in all ages ſo long as the world ſhall laſt, King <hi>Iames</hi> the ſixt of that name in <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp; firſt of that name in <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland;</hi> God gaue your L. ſuch favour in the ſight of that Prince &amp; beſtowed vpon you ſuch gifts of mynd &amp; body as did indeed merit at that princes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, al the degrees of honor and great eſtate, which that royall and magnifick Prince rewarded your L. ſervice withall. For I may ſay truely: your L. was faithful to his Majeſty and when his Hyenes did honour your L to be Captaine of a guard for the peace of the countrie and for execution of juſtice, to the well of his Majesties ſubjects, againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, bangſters, contemners of his Heines lawes &amp; autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. Your L. did with ſuch courage and conſcience ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrat that charge that you ſpared not great nor ſmall untill that they were brought vnder obedience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:25087:3"/>gaue your L. grace in your old age, to retire your ſelf fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Court, with as great honour, wealth and favour of your Prince, and more, then any other did, as I could marke in my time. Moreover, God hath given to your L. ability &amp; will to honour your countrie, in building of faire Palaces, and planting faire Ortchards &amp; gardens in the places of your L. reſidences: In being magnifick in Hoſpitalitie, both to honourable ſtrangers comming to ſee this country, &amp; to our owne countrie men, noble, ignoble, friends &amp; acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Lyke as God hath made your L. the man to ſet vp againe that houſe whereof your L. came, and to raiſe the ruynes thereof to as good estate as ever it was; Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of your L. liberalitie in advancing your friends to great honours and heritages, to bee injoyed by them as your L. ſucceſſours, when you ſhall depart from this life. I know not what more is requyred to make your L. both heere and eternally happie: but that your L. remember &amp; conſider this good &amp; gratious providence of God toward you, and bee thankfull, ſaying with <hi>David, What ſhal I render to GOD for all his benefites to me, &amp;c. Pſ. 116.</hi> And confeſſe to God your ſinnes with ſorrow for them, and to belieue his promiſes of mercie to penitent ſinners throgh the merit of his beloved Son Ieſus Christ: that with old <hi>Iacob, Gen. 49</hi> and <hi>Simeon, Luk. 2.</hi> waiting for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Lord, your L. may depart in peace in Gods appoynted tyme. To you my Lord I dedicat this little Treatiſe, as having no kinſman now ſo neare vnto mee by blood, or ſo honourable in estate: which I recommend vnto your L. gratious acceptation and your L. ſelfe, to the grace of GOD. And reſts,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your L cooſin to honour and ſerue you in the LORD to my power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25087:3"/>
            <head>To the loving Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>LOving Chriſtian Reader, wit: when long ſickneſſe brought v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon mee ſo great inability and weakneſſe, that I was not able to goe without doores, farre leſſe to proſecute the diſpenſation of my miniſtrie in publick: I ſet my ſelfe at the intervals of any little reſpiration from paine, to the reading and meditating of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the light of knowledge and faith might more and more ſhyne in my mynde, and abyde in my memory, and the ſenſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ioy and peace, might poſſeſſe my heart and conſcience: For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly: As water if it ſtand long and runne not, want good aire or lyvelie ſpring, will rotte and ſtinke: So the ſoule of man if it bee not mooving about good, and mooved by the breath of the holy Spirit, that it may bee a <hi>well of water of lyfe: Ioh.</hi> 7.38. It will ſoone die in corruption and ſinne, and ſtinke in the noſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les of GOD <hi>Deut. 32.19.</hi> Amongſt other Scriptures I read theſe Songs contained in this little Treatiſe, and did meditate vpon them: I wrote my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, which when I ſhew them to ſome godly learned Brethren, they thought if they were publiſhed they might do good to others. I thinke my ſelfe that they may ſerue for good vſe, to two ſorts of people: Firſt to good Chriſtian men and women, who delyte to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate in the Law of GOD both day and night. <hi>Pſ. 1.</hi> Next to yong ſtudents of Theologie, aſpyring to be Preachers and Miniſters of Gods word: The particulars ſet down in order in this Treatiſe ſerveth to help ſuch. For <hi>1.</hi> a yong Divyne ſhould be acquaint in ſome good meaſure, with the originall languages wherein the holy Scriptures were firſt writen, namely the Hebrew and Greeke that he may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>Id eſt</hi> and <hi>Hoc eſt</hi> of everie word of his Text, and not to be addicted to any one mans interpretation; ſo in a manner living by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mans faith, but labour to haue in himſelfe, a full plerophory of faith. 2. Hee ſhould labour to make plaine the Hebraiſmes and Helleniſmes in holy Scripture by proper paraphraſe to the purpoſe. 3. Hee ſhould take good heed to his method in preaching. Loving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25087:4"/>There bee chiefely one of two methods that the beſt preachers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in preaching The one cryptick, the other open, or by the practiſe of Logicall analyſis. The 2 I preferre to the 1. for theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. 1. The Cryptik method requyreth long practiſe, a great witte and memorie: which yongue ſcollers cannot ſuddenly attaine vnto. 2. The Cryptick method doth more mooue the affections, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the minde, ſo that after ſuch Sermons are well delyvered, if yee will aske the auditors iudgement thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they will ſay to you, that the man preached verie well, but they haue forgote what hee ſaid: but the open method vſed by a good man and of good vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſerveth to teach, delyte, mooue, both himſelfe and his hearers, and to helpe their memories. 3. The Cryptick method being in continuall diſcourſe maketh not the vſes of the word mentioned by the Apoſtle: <hi>2. Tim. 3.16.</hi> But the open method, may verie well vſe the word accordingly, when grounds for the vſes are found in the Text. And this purpoſe my analyſis reſpects. The 4. vſe a yongue Divyne may make of this booke, is: hee may learne in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp the ſumme of his text, to ſee that it bee it indeed, and not a ſumme of purpoſes, flying firſt to his phantaſie which hee maketh the ſumme of the text. The 5. vſe is to teach him to draw out his doctrines properly out of the words or purpoſe of the text either as Apodeictik concluſions or by way of neceſſarie conſequence, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefrom: &amp; not make <hi>quid libet ex quolibet.</hi> Seeing the whole word of God is full of principals which ſhould not bee denyed. For if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> was eneugh to <hi>Pithagoras</hi> ſchollers: How much more ſhould <hi>Thus ſayeth the LORD:</hi> bee eneugh to all men, fearing God and loving him. The 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vſe is to teach him to put a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, betwixt <hi>Methodum textus,</hi> and <hi>Methodum doctrinae:</hi> that is to ſay, that this method bee, by the naturall logick analyſis of the text: whither in ſimple enunciations, propoſitions, Enthememes, or Syllogiſmes, conſidering well ſubiects and attributs, whether they bee proper, or figurat, examining the force of the words in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, comparing Scripture with Scripture: ſo ſhall hee haue many doores open to him for varietie of doctrine, and ſhall bee ſaved from confuſion and idle repetition of purpoſes. A practicall glance of theſe vſes I giue in this Treatiſe: How well or ill, I ſubmit my ſelfe to thy charitable iudgement. Now commending mee to thy prayers to God for mee; that I may fight out the good ſight of faith, &amp; finiſh my courſe with ioy. I commend thee to the grace of GOD.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:25087:4"/>
            <head>AD ORNATISSIMVM VIRVM, <hi>D. GVLIELMVM MORAVIVM</hi> hujus libelli &amp; alterius, non ita pridem <hi>de morte editi, Authorem.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>AEGro fallebat curas de morte libellus:</l>
            <l>Nunc hymnis laeto cor tibi ritè ſalit.</l>
            <l>Dum <hi>Muſas</hi> ſacro deducis fonte <hi>novenas,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Illuſtraſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> tuo liberiore stylo.</l>
            <l>Verum doctrinae Methodum, juveni<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſeni<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>
            </l>
            <l>Indigitas, <hi>Moravi,</hi> ſimplicitate piâ.</l>
            <l>Olim voce gregem paſcebas ſedulus; at jam</l>
            <l>Pagina, quà liceat, paſcit amoena tua.</l>
            <l>Eia age, nè pigeat ſaeclis prodeſſe futuris;</l>
            <l>Hic animos recreat moeſta<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> corda labor.</l>
            <l>Dignus luce cluet, meruit virtute ſuperſtes</l>
            <l>Qui bene de cunctis, poſt obitum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> meret.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>ROBERTVS CRAFORDUS</hi> alias <hi>Lunnaeus.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:25087:5"/>
            <head>The names and number of Songs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. THE ſong of <hi>Moſes</hi> at the red Sea. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15</item>
               <item>II. The ſong of <hi>Moſes</hi> before his death. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.</item>
               <item>III. The ſong of <hi>Deborah. Iudg.</hi> 5.</item>
               <item>IIII. The ſong of <hi>Channa.</hi> I. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.</item>
               <item>V. The ſong of <hi>Hezechiah</hi> King of Iudah. <hi>Eſay</hi> 38.</item>
               <item>VI. The ſong of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Marie. Luk.</hi> I.</item>
               <item>VII. The ſong of <hi>Zacharie. Luk.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>VIII. The ſong of Angels at the birth of CHRIST. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.</item>
               <item>IX. The ſong of <hi>Simeon. Luk.</hi> 2.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="song_book">
            <pb facs="tcp:25087:5"/>
            <head>The ſong of Moſes, Miriam and all Iſraell when they had paſſed through the red Sea. <hi>Exod. 15.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="text">
                  <head>The Text.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                     </hi> Will ſing to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah for hee hath excelled wonderfully: The horſe and his ryder hee hath throwne in the Sea.</p>
                  <p>Iah is my strength and ſong: and hee was my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. This is my ſtrong GOD, and I will make him a tabernacle; the GOD of my fathers I ſhal exalt him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:25087:6"/>IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH is a man of warre, IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH is his name.</p>
                  <p>Pharoahs charets and his host hath hee cast into the Sea: And his choſen captaines are drowned in the red Sea.</p>
                  <p>The deepths hath covered them, they diſcended to the bottom as a stone.</p>
                  <p>Thy right hand Iehovah is magnified in strength thy right hand Iehovah; hath broken in peices the enemy</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:25087:6"/>And in the greatneſſe of thy excellencie, thou hath everthrowne thoſe that roſe vp against thee; thou ſent forth thy wrath which conſumed them as ſtuble.</p>
                  <p>And with the blaſt of thy noſthirles the waters were gathered together, the floods ſtood as a heape, the deepths were congea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the heart of the ſea.</p>
                  <p>The enemie had ſaid, I will purſue, I wil overtake, I will devyde the spoyle, I ſhall haue my heart ſyth of them, I will draw my ſword, my hand ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy them.</p>
                  <p>Thou did blow with thy winde, the ſea covered them, they ſanke as lead
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25087:7"/>in mightie waters.</p>
                  <p>Who is like vnto thee IE-HOVAH amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the gods: Who is like vnto thee, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in holineſſe, feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full with praiſes, working wonders?</p>
                  <p>Thou streatched out thy right hand, the earth ſwallowed them.</p>
                  <p>Thou leads in thy mercie this people whom thou hath redeemed: Thou guydeth in thy strength to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of thy holineſſe.</p>
                  <p>The people ſhal heare: they ſhall bee astoniſhed: So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhall take hold vpon the inhabitants of Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stina.</p>
                  <p>The Dukes of Edome ſhall bee amazed, feare ſhall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25087:7"/>take hold vpon the strong men of Moab, all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of Canaan ſhall melt away.</p>
                  <p>Feare and dread ſhall fall vpon them by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy arme, they ſhal bee still as a ſtone, vntill the people paſſe by, IEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH: vntill the people paſſe by, which thou hast purcheſed.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhall bring them to it, and plant them in the mountaine of thy inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: Iehovah, which thou made for a dwelling place, in the ſanctuarie which thy hands haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed.</p>
                  <p>IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH ſhall reigne for ever and ever.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="paraphrase">
                  <pb facs="tcp:25087:5"/>
                  <head>The paraphraſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HO can but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the power goodneſſe, and juſtice of our GOD: how can I the leader of this people, or they, ceaſe to ſing and rejoyce, ſeeing IEHOVAH the onely true God, our God, hath drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Sea <hi>Phoroahs</hi> charets and horſes with all his armie which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſewed vs.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Hee hath ever beene my ſtrong defender whoſe name is IAH: but now he hath wonderfully delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs from a mighty &amp; cruell tyranne, therefore hee is the ſubject of my ſong, hee is our ſtrong
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25087:6"/>GOD, &amp; the GOD of our fathers, wee will exalt him and honour him, &amp; publickly worſhip him,</p>
                  <p n="3">3. IEHOVAH is a Lord mighty in battell as his Name ſhowes ſignifying one that hath being in himſelfe, and hath given beeing to all creatures; and is well called the LORD of Hoaſts.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A document heereof is this overthrow of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah with his ſtrong cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets, the drovning of him: of them, of his choyſe captaines and whole ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie in the red ſea.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. High was their pryde but their perſons lyeth low in the ſea: Their ſwimming ſerveth them to no more vſe than the ſtones, which caſt in the water plump downe to the ground.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. O LORD thou alone art ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, thou alone O Lord art able to daſh in peices all thy enemies.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:25087:6"/>7. And ſo great is thy excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie that thou over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweſt all thoſe that ryſe vp againſt thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for thou accounts ſuch to ryſe vp againſt thy ſelfe: Thy wrath breakes foorth vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as fyre, and before it they are as ſtuble before the fyre.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Thou being moved with the diſtres of thy people, and rage of the enemie, &amp; with the prayer of Moſes ſent foorth a mighty eaſt wind which divided the ſea in two and made dry land in the mids thereof for thy people to paſſe thorow.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. And this thou did o Lord in the midſt of the pryde and rage of the enemie, in the hight of their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and hope to bring vs back to be their perpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall ſlaves.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. But thou diſapointed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a winde, which made a dry way for thy
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25087:7"/>people, and with the ſea which turned and drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them all,</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Let all the mightie that ever were ſo accounted be rehearſed, which of them may bee compared with thee O LORD, in holines or goodnes, in acts praiſe worthie and wonderfull.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. By thy mightie power the ſea which drowned them was made the place of their buriall.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Now haſt thou begun to lead thy people whom of thy free mercie thou haſt redeemed: now thou haſt begun to guyde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the place, where thy holyneſſe promiſed to dwell in the mids of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. This thy worke O Lord ſhall not reſt heere, but thou ſhal ſtrik with feare other nations, and with ſorrow the Paleſtins, whom thou haſt appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a prey for thy people</p>
                  <p n="15">15. The Princes of Edom, the ſtrong men of Moab,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25087:7"/>and all the heathen who know not and ſerue not thee, ſhall feare, chieflie the Canaanits curſed of olde and deſtinate to be rooted out by thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Iſraell.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Thou ſhall worke with them ſo powerfully, that they ſhall bee as ſtones, neither ſpeaking nor mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, vntill all thy people paſſe by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom thou haſt ſet at liberty, to place them in the land appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for them,</p>
                  <p n="17">17. To holy Canaan ſhalt thou bring them, which thou keepes as an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for them, where thou will dwell amongſt them, and by thy preſence ſanctifie &amp; eſtabliſh both it and them.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. IEHOVAH who now hath kythed to bee our King, of his Kingdome there ſhall bee no end.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:25087:8"/>
                  <head>The argument and analyſis of this Song.</head>
                  <p>THis Song Moſes and all Iſrael ſung to the praiſe of God, the day after the Lord led them through the red Sea on dry land, and after the Lord cauſed the waters returne vpon Pharaohs chariots &amp; horſemen, who perſued and followed his people, and therewith drowned them all.</p>
                  <p>The parts of this Song are three: 1. a preface, verſe 1. next the purpoſe of the ſong from the 1. verſe to the 18. Thirdly the concluſion, verſe 18. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face containes three things. 1. the maker and vptaker of the Song, to wit Moſes in theſe words, <hi>I will ſing.</hi> 2. the perſon in whoſe praiſe this Song was made &amp; ſung in theſe wordes; <hi>to Iehovah.</hi> 3. a reaſon of the making and vptaking of this ſong and praiſing of the Lord thereby, and it hath two parts: the 1 taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods excellencie generally in theſe wordes, <hi>for hee hath excelled wonderfully.</hi> the 2. taken from a preſent particular document of his excellency in theſe words <hi>the horſe and his rider hath hee throwne in the Sea.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The purpoſe of this Song containes two thinges. 1. the praiſe of God, from the beginning of the 2. ver. to the 14 Secondly, a Propheſie of the conſequents of this great worke in bringing his people through the red Sea on dry land, and drowning Pharoah and his whole armie who purſued his people. The praiſe of God is expreſſed, 1. by the cauſes preſently mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to praiſe him. 2. by a vowe, heerafter by word and deede to be thankfull to him verſe 2. Next they praiſe God by enumeration of argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of his praiſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25087:8"/>from the 2. ver. to the 14. Thoſe arguments are eight in number, the 1, is taken from his valour, in theſe wordes: <hi>the Lord is a mightie Warriour.</hi> the 2. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the 1. is taken from his Name, in theſe wordes, <hi>Iehovah is his Name.</hi> This name imports his eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, his trueth in performing his promiſes, his beeing to bee of himſelf and no other, and that hee gives be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all creatures: and therfore able to deſtroy them againe when he pleaſes, ver. 3. The third argument of his praiſe is taken from the worke preſently done vpon Pharaoh and his hoſte, verſe 4.5. The fourth argument of his praiſe is taken from his power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct with his juſtice in deſtroying his enemies, and ſuch as roſe vp againſt him, verſe 6.7. The fifth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of his praiſe is taken from his power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct with his goodneſſe to his people, verſe 8. The ſixth argument of his praiſe is taken from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of this work of God, with the preſumption and pride of the enemy, who thought and ſaid all was in his power, but God blew with his wind, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the waters drown him and his armie, verſe, 9.10.</p>
                  <p>The 7. argument of his praiſe is taken from the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereminencie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of GOD above all men in the world who ſeeme mightie; and this ſupereminencie is ſet downe in three particulars: Holineſſe, fearefullneſſe, wonderfulneſſe, all kything in this worke: His holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in delivering his people from a mightie &amp; cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell Tyranne: his fearefulneſſe in deſtroying the tyran and his whole army together; his wonderfulneſſe in divyding the Sea, making his people to goe through the middeſt of it vpon dry ground, and making their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25087:9"/>enemies by wind and water therein to drowne, verſe 11.12. The 8. argument of his praiſe is taken from his mercie and trueth to his people, beginning with this work to manifeſt the ſame, and to confirme their faith and hope of performing his promiſe made to their fathers, verſe 13. The propheſie of the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of this work of God containes three things. 1. concerning the nations by whoſe land the people of Iſrael ſhould paſſe to the land of promiſe, namely the Edomites and Moabites, that feare and aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould fall vpon them, &amp; force them to let his people paſſe by. The 2. concernes the inhabitants of Paleſtina, &amp; chiefly the Canaanits, that their hearts ſhould melt away for feare, verſe 14.15.16. The 3. thing in the prophecie concernes GODS people, That God ſhould bring them vnto, poſſeſſe them in, as their inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the land promiſed to their fathers, and dwell amongſt them by the meanes of his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick viſible worſhip, verſe 17. The concluſion of the ſong is that the Kingdome of God is everlaſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="annotations">
                  <head>Annotations vpon this Song.</head>
                  <p>Verſe 1. <hi>I will ſing:</hi> not onlie for to witneſſe our thankfulneſe to God for our deliverance: but alſo for confirmation of the trueth of this Hiſtorie; for ſixe hundreth thouſand men, with their wives and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren bore witneſſe in ſigning this Song.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto Iehovah;</hi> that is vnto his praiſe: ſo Pſal. 106. ver. 12. compare this ſong, with the ſong, Apoc. 15. ver. 2.3.4. both ſung at the Sea: Harpes of timbrels
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25087:9"/>in the ſingers hands: The ſongs are of Moſes and of the Lambe, the one delivered from the bondage and perſecution of Pharaoh: the other from the beaſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, or the Pope.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 2. <hi>IAH,</hi> a proper name of God firſt menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned on in holy Scripture, next Pſal. 68.5. In Greek in the new Teſtament it is joyned to <hi>Halelu</hi> to make <hi>Haleluiah,</hi> that is, Praiſe yee the Lord; the whole compond word is originally Hebrew, ſee Apoc. 19.1.3.4.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Strength:</hi> ſo ſignifieth the Hebrew word properly: yet ſeing it is joyned heere with theſe words, &amp; ſung: it ſignifieth the ſtrength of ſong and praiſe, that is, moſt vehement praiſe: So Chriſt, Math. 21.16. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poneth this word, vſed Pſal. 8.2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My GOD:</hi> this oppones the true GOD to Idols, the religion of his people to the errour and idolatrie of other nations, as in the next words Abrahams re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion oppoſit to the ſuperſtition of the nations, ſee Eſay 25.9.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 3. <hi>A man of Warre,</hi> that is, a notable War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour: for the word Man added to other things in the Hebrew phraſe often ſignifieth excellencie, ſee Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. 4.10. Iob 22.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH,</hi> this name imports: 1. Gods eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp; is in Greek expreſſed by α and ω Apoc. 1.8.2. it ſignifieth his power above all creatures, and over them, as having beeing of himſelfe only, and giving beeing to all creatures, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. Thirdly, it ſignifies his trueth in performing his promiſe, Exod. 6. 3. Fourthly, his power in executing judgement on the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25087:10"/>enemies of his Church, and Hee therefore called <hi>Iehovah</hi> of Hoſts. Pſal. 83.14.19. and 46.7.8.12.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 5. <hi>As a ſtone:</hi> that is to ſaye, their skill in ſwimming did ſerve them to no vſe.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 6. <hi>Thy right hand, thy right hand:</hi> this dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling imports that this miraculous work can neither bee aſcribed to fortoun, nor to the induſtrie of men, but to GOD onely.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 6. <hi>Againſt thee</hi> the Chaldaick paraphraſe hath <hi>againſt thy people:</hi> ſee Zach. 2.8. Mat. 25.45. Act 9.4.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 8. <hi>Blaſt:</hi> hee meaneth that Eaſt wind ſpoken of before Chap. 14.2.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 11. <hi>GODS:</hi> that is, Princes or Potentates, ſee Pſal. 82. and 89.7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Purchaſed:</hi> in Hebrew Canah, which ſignifieth getting by generation. Gen. 41. or buying. Gen. 25.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations of grounds for vſe and doctrine.</head>
                  <p>Obſ. 1. HOly ſongs have beene in vſe in the true Church in all ages, and are recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Chriſtian Church. Eph. 5.19. Col. 3.16. Iam. 5.13. But the vſe of Muſicall inſtruments not ſo: as being ceremoniall types in the old Teſtament prefiguring the joy of the holy Ghoſt aboundantlye to bee powred out vpon Chriſtians vnder the New Teſtament. Rom. 14.17. Eph. 5.19.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 2. This ſong proves the veritie of the whole
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25087:10"/>hiſtory preceeding in the book of Ex. ſeing not only Moyſes ſung it, but with him ſixe hundreth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men beſyde women and bairnes, whereof any two or three might haue beene witneſſes againſt Moſes, if this had beene fabulous: Heere I might take occaſion to diſpute that the holy Scripture is true and the very true word of GOD: but my purpoſe is not in this treatiſe to diſpute contraverſies.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 3. We haue here an example to teach vs to be thankfull to GOD for his benefites and of ſolemne thankſgiving, if common to one Church or to the vniverſall.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 4. vpon. verſe. 1. Moſes is firſt and formeſt in this thankſgiving, by reaſon of his place: by his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple teaching al ſuch as God hath raiſed vp too hy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in church or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth to do the like</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 5. There is no worke of GOD in creation or providence, wherein ſome one or moe of his attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buts doth not ſhew themſelfe, thought ſome more clearely then other, vpon which wee ſhould chiefly meditat: So worſhipping GOD by this mids of his worſhip; as Moſes and the people doeth heere me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditat vpon his excellencie, ſupereminence, power, juſtice, mercie, goodneſſe, holineſſe, ttueth: which all kythed in the worke of their deliverance.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 6. All delyverance from danger, all good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in affairs, all ſalvation temporarie or eternall: flowes to vs from GOD of his mercie without our merits, therefore to him onely belongs the praiſe,</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 7. Wee ſhould ſtudie by all meanes, to put a difference betwixt the true GOD and Idols, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25087:11"/>wee may know him, ſerue him, and worſhip him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. Io. 4.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 8. vpon verſ. 2. They praiſe GOD vpon theſe three grounds. 1. Vpon the ſence of their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience &amp; experience. 2. Vpon the duety which they profeſſe and promiſe of their thankfulneſſe in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping him publickly. Vpon their obligation of all ſort of homage to him: So ſhould wee meditat v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon grounds of reaſons to praiſe GOD that we may ſhow our ſelves thankfull for his benefites.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 9. GOD is compared to a moſt mightie man of warre, to teach vs both to feare him and truſt in him, becauſe hee is able to deſtroy all ſuch as ryſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, ſee thee hiſtorie of <hi>Senacherib</hi> with <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah,</hi> and of the nations with <hi>Iehoſophat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Obſ. 10. GOD accounts the wrong done to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to bee done to himſelfe. Act, 9.4. And the good done to them to bee done to him. Mat. 25, 40. This ſhould comfort the godly and affray wicked perſecuters.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 11. vpon verſ. 9. The wicked ſing the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph before the victorie, and when their pryde is at the hight then comes ſuddenly their deſtruction. Pſalme. 73.18.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 12. verſ. 10.11.12. All the creatures are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to GOD except the deuils and mankynd: and ſerue him in ſaving his ſervants, and deſtroying their enemies whenſoever GOD bids them.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 13. vpon verſ. 13. The worke of grace and ſalvation once begun by GOD in his children, he will never leaue till hee perfyte it. Pſal. 138. 8. Phil. 1.8.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25087:11"/>Therefore wee ſhould not diſpare vnder the ſenſe of deſertion: Neither is the doctrine of the finall and totall apoſtaſie of the ſancts true but hereticall.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 14. GOD is able to defend his people from their enemies, were they never ſo many &amp; mighty.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 15. vpon verſ. 18. The times, places, and perſons, of GODS Church, when, where, and by whom he will be worſhipped he himſelfe ordaines.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 16. vpon verſ. 18. The continuance of the Church of GOD is grounded vpon his everlaſting Kingdome. Pſal. 102 29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="song">
                  <head>This ſong in meeter followeth to be ſung with the tune of the <hi>25.</hi> Pſalme.</head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>Verſe. 1.</head>
                     <l>FOR joy now will I ſing,</l>
                     <l>to IEHOVAH a ſong,</l>
                     <l>For wonderfully hath hee now,</l>
                     <l>excelled in the throng</l>
                     <l>Of horſemen: whom hee hath</l>
                     <l>throwne downe vnto the ſea,</l>
                     <l>Pharaoh the king I meane,</l>
                     <l>and all his great armie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>Verſ. 2.</head>
                     <l>The ſubject of my ſong,</l>
                     <l>I ſee that IAH muſt bee</l>
                     <l>My ſtrength and my ſalvation,</l>
                     <l>ſtill is and ſo was hee:</l>
                     <l>This is my, GOD moſt ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>to him Ile make a tent:</l>
                     <l>My Fathers GOD hee is alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:25087:12"/>
                     <head>Verſ. 3.</head>
                     <l>A mightie man of warre,</l>
                     <l>IEHOVAH is I ſay,</l>
                     <l>No marvell, for IEHOVAH is</l>
                     <l>his name and ſhall bee ay.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <head>Verſ. 4.</head>
                     <l>Pharoahs charets and hoſt,</l>
                     <l>Hee caſt into the ſea,</l>
                     <l>Choſen captaines were drowned there</l>
                     <l>in mids of the red ſea.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>Verſ. 5.</head>
                     <l>The deepe them covered all,</l>
                     <l>downe to the ground they ſanke,</l>
                     <l>Even lyke as doth a ſtone,</l>
                     <l>that is caſt in a ſtanke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="6">
                     <head>Verſ. 6.</head>
                     <l>IEHOVAH thy right hand,</l>
                     <l>in ſtrength is excellent:</l>
                     <l>For thy right hand IEHOVAH hath,</l>
                     <l>thy foes in peices rent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="7">
                     <head>Verſ. 7.</head>
                     <l>And in the greatneſſe of</l>
                     <l>thy power now thou haſt,</l>
                     <l>Subdued thoſe, gainſt thee that roſe,</l>
                     <l>for downe thou haſt them caſt.</l>
                     <l>Thy wrath thou did ſend foorth,</l>
                     <l>conſuming them as fyre</l>
                     <l>Conſumeth ſtuble where it comes.</l>
                     <l>ſo hote was then thine ire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="8">
                     <head>Verſ. 8</head>
                     <l>And with the blaſt of thy</l>
                     <l>noſtriles the water ſtood,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:25087:12"/>Gathr'd together on a heap,</l>
                     <l>and ſo did ſtay the flood</l>
                     <l>In midſt of the ſea,</l>
                     <l>The deep congealed then,</l>
                     <l>So mightie was thy eaſter wind,</l>
                     <l>dry way it made to men.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="9">
                     <head>Verſ. 9.</head>
                     <l>The enemie had ſaid,</l>
                     <l>I will oretake, I will</l>
                     <l>Divyde the ſpoyle, I ſhall haue my</l>
                     <l>heart ſytht on them with ill.</l>
                     <l>My ſword I will draw out,</l>
                     <l>and then my hand ſhall make,</l>
                     <l>This people my inheritance,</l>
                     <l>my yoke they ſhall not ſhake,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="10">
                     <head>Verſ 10</head>
                     <l>Then with thy wind thou blew</l>
                     <l>the ſea them all did hyde,</l>
                     <l>They ſanke as lead in waters deepe,</l>
                     <l>ſo cruell was the tyde,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="11">
                     <head>Verſ 11</head>
                     <l>Who is lyke vnto thee,</l>
                     <l>the mightie all among?</l>
                     <l>IEHOVE I ſay who is the lyke?</l>
                     <l>I ſay that there is none.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thy glorie is ſo great,</l>
                     <l>and thou ſo holy art,</l>
                     <l>With praiſes to bee reverenc'd,</l>
                     <l>thy wonders make vs ſtart</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="12">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:25087:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <head>¶ 12.</head>
                     <l>When thou dideſt ſtreatch out</l>
                     <l>thy right hand ſuddenly:</l>
                     <l>The loweſt earth did then thy foes,</l>
                     <l>vp ſwallow by and by.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="13">
                     <head>Verſ. 13.</head>
                     <l>Thou leads in thy mercie,</l>
                     <l>thus thy redeemed people,</l>
                     <l>Thou guyds them alſo in thy ſtrength</l>
                     <l>vnto thy holy ſtaple.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="14">
                     <head>Verſ. 14.</head>
                     <l>So ſoone as nations</l>
                     <l>ſhall heare, then ſhall they ſhake,</l>
                     <l>Paleſtina's inhabitants,</l>
                     <l>ſhall doole and ſorrow make.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="15">
                     <head>Verſ. 15.</head>
                     <l>The Dukes of Edom then,</l>
                     <l>amazed all ſhall bee:</l>
                     <l>Moabs ſtrong men ſhall melt away,</l>
                     <l>And Canaans poſteritie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="16">
                     <head>Verſ. 16.</head>
                     <l>Such feare &amp; dread ſhall fall</l>
                     <l>on them of thy right hand,</l>
                     <l>That as a ſtone they ſhall ly ſtill,</l>
                     <l>till Iſraell paſſe their land.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="17">
                     <head>Verſ. 17.</head>
                     <l>IEHOVAH, thou ſhall bring,</l>
                     <l>and plant them in the hill,</l>
                     <l>Of thy holy inheritance,</l>
                     <l>a place where thou'le dwell ſtill,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſanctuarie there,</l>
                     <l>thy hands haue made to byde,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="18">
                     <head>Verſ. 18.</head>
                     <l>Iehovah alone ſhall reigne,</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:25087:13"/>
               <head>The Song of MOYSES before his death. Deut. <hi>32.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>Text.</head>
                  <p>GIve eare yee Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and I will speake: and heare O earth the words of my mouth.</p>
                  <p>My doctrine ſhall drop as the raine, my speach ſhall diſtill as the dew, as the ſmall rain vpon the tender hearbe, and as ſhowres v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the graſſe.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe I will publiſh the name of IEHOVAH, Aſcribe yee greatneſſe to our GOD.</p>
                  <p>The rock, his work is perfit, for all his wayes are judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: a strong God faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and without iniquitie, juſt and right is hee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:25087:14"/>Hee hath corrupted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; their spot is not his childrens, a perverſe, and crooked generation.</p>
                  <p>Doe yee ſo requyte IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH! O yee fooliſh people and vnwiſe: Is not hee thy Father? Thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer? Hath he not made thee, and eſtabliſht thee?</p>
                  <p>Remember the dayes of old the yeares of generation &amp; generation, aske thy father and hee will ſhew thee, thy elders &amp; they will tell thee.</p>
                  <p>The hie one in diſtributing heritage to the Nations, in ſeparating the ſons of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, hee ſet the bounds of the people, to the number of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25087:14"/>the children of Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>For the portion of IEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH is his people, IA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COB the line of his heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
                  <p>Hee found him in the land of Wilderneſſe, and in a waſte and howling Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: hee cauſed him goe about: hee taught him: he kept him as the apple of his eye.</p>
                  <p>As the Eagle stirreth vp her nest, flightereth over her birds, ſpreads out her wings, takes it, beares it vpon her wing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:25087:15"/>Iehovah alone led him, and there was no ſtrange god with him.</p>
                  <p>Hee made him ryde vpon the hie places of the earth; and hee ate the increaſe of the field: and hee made him to ſucke honie out of the rock, and oyle out of the flint of the rocke.</p>
                  <p>Butter of Kyne, and milke of Sheepe, with fat of lambs and Rams ſons of Baſhan, with the fat of the neares of wheat, and the red blood of the wine berry thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt drinke.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>I</hi> eſchurun grew fat and flang, thou hast growne fat, thou haſt grown groſſe, thou covered thee: and hee left GOD that made him the rocke of his ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:25087:15"/>They provoked him to je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſie with strange gods: they provocked him to anger with abominations.</p>
                  <p>They ſacrificed to Devils, not vnto GOD, to gods whom they knew not, to new gods neare hand whom your fathers feared not.</p>
                  <p>Of the rocke that begatte thee: thou art forgetfull: and hath forgot the GOD that brought thee foorth of the wombe.</p>
                  <p>And IEHOVAH ſaw it and hee abdicat through indignation his ſonnes and his daughters.</p>
                  <p>And hee ſaid, I will hide my face from them, I ſhall ſee what will bee their end:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25087:16"/>for they are a froward ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, children in whom is no fidelitie.</p>
                  <p>They haue provoked me to jealouſie with that which was not God, they haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked mee to anger with their vanities, and I ſhall provoke them to jealouſie with thoſe that are not a people: I ſhal provoke them to anger with a fooliſh nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>For a fyre is kindled in my anger, and ſhall burne to hell, and ſhall conſume the earth, with the increaſe therof, &amp; ſhal ſet on fire the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the mountains. I will joyne evils togother vpon them, I will spend my arrows vpon them,</p>
                  <p>Burnt with hunger, eaten vp with burning coale, and bitter deſtruction, &amp; teeth of beaſts wil I ſend againſt them, with the poyſon of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents of the duſt.</p>
                  <p>Without, the ſword ſhall make fatherleſſe in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25087:16"/>chambers, feare ſhall overtake the choyſe younge man, and the Virgin, the ſuckling child, with the gray-haird man.</p>
                  <p>I ſaid, I ſhall ſcatter them in corners I ſhall make the memorie of them to ceaſe from men.</p>
                  <p>Were not I feared the wrath of the enemy leaſt their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries ſhould behaue themſelues ſtrangely, leaſt they ſhould ſay, our hie hand, and IEHOVAHS hath not wrought all this. For they are a nation voyd of counſell, and hath no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in them.</p>
                  <p>Oh that they were wiſe, that they vnderſtood this: that they vnderstood their latter end.</p>
                  <p>How ſhould one chaſe a thouſand, or two put ten thouſand to flight, if not becauſe their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25087:17"/>Rocke had ſold them, and IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH cauſed them yeeld them ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>For their rocke is not as our ROCKE, even our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies being judges.</p>
                  <p>For their vine is of the vine of Sodom, and of the fields of Gomorah, their graps, are grapes of venome, they haue bitter cluſters.</p>
                  <p>Their wine is the venome of Dragons, and the cruell head of Aspes.</p>
                  <p>Is not this laid vp beſide me: ſealed among my trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
                  <p>Vengeance is myne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe: in time their foot ſhall stagger, for the day of their destruction is neare, and haſtneth things to come to them.</p>
                  <p>For IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH ſhall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25087:17"/>judge his people and ſhall repent himſelfe for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, when hee ſhall ſee the hand is gone &amp; nothing ſhut vp or left.</p>
                  <p>And hee ſhall ſay where are their gods, the rocke wherein they truſted?</p>
                  <p>Who did eate the fatte of their ſacrifices, dranke the wine of their brunt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, let them ryſe &amp; help you: let them bee your hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
                  <p>See now that I, I my ſelfe and no gods with mee: I cauſe to die, and I cauſe to liue, I wound, and I heale, and there is none can pluck out of my hand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:25087:18"/>For I lift vp my hand to the Heavens and ſay: I liue for ever.</p>
                  <p>If I ſharpe my glittering ſword, and my hand take hold on judgement, I will render vengeance to my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies and recompenſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hate mee.</p>
                  <p>I will make my arrows drunke with blood (and my ſword ſhall eat fleſh) of the blood of the ſlaine, and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie, from the beginning of revenges vpon the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</p>
                  <p>Yee nations praiſe his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for hee will auenge the blood of his ſervants, and render vengeance to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries: and will be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to his land and to his people.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="paraphrase">
                  <pb facs="tcp:25087:13"/>
                  <head>Paraphraſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. IF you people will not hearken to my words, the Heavens and Earth, &amp; all creatures other ſhall be witneſſes againſt you.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If my people bee a ſoft ſoyle, and good ground, my doctrine ſhall be fruit full in young and olde, in weake and ſtrong.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Glorifie God in hearken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his word, for I will make him manifeſt to you, who howbeit hee be alwayes infinite, yet hee abaſes him to be our God &amp; his will I will declare.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. To whome will yee goe from this God? who is ſo ſtronge, ſo righteous in all his actions, ſo true in all his wordes, and in whom no defect can bee found?</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:25087:14"/>5. Yet Iſrael hath corrupted his owne wayes, which proveth they are not the children of GOD, but a wicked and perverſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Is this the reward where with ye reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence God? who hath adopted you to be his children, when ye were his enemies, paſſing by the reſt of mankinde who were as ſib to him by creation as you, who hath redeemed you from the bondage of Egypt, &amp; hath magnified you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove other people, when you were worſe than no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The hiſtorie of Abraham Iſaak and ſacob and of the reſt of your predeceſſors, ſhewes your ſmall be gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp; Gods great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy &amp; goodnes toward you</p>
                  <p n="8">8. When God in his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence allotted to everi nation a dwelling place he had minde of Iſrael and appointed for their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25087:14"/>a place moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and moſt excellent.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. For hee had freelie cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the poſteritie of Iacob to bee his peculiar people beſide all the World.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. When they were in a Wilderneſſe where there was neither bread, nor water, nor other thing to ſuſtaine their life, GOD fed them, and clad them, and becauſe of their infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie he cauſed them go about the Wilderneſſe fourtie yeares: during the which time, hee taught them by his benefites and chaſtiſments: yet hee had exceeding great care of them to keep them from all hurt.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. And look wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> care the Eagle or any other fowle have of their young ones in hatching them, cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them vntill they can come foorth or flee, and guiding them from the neſt: ſuch care had God of his people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:25087:15"/>12. Hee needed not the helpe of any other beſyde him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, &amp; would haue none: for hee would haue the guyding of his people to himſelfe alone.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Hee placed him in Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an an hillie countrie, &amp; full of fertill valleyes: whoſe craigie places were no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> barren, but there was to bee found honnie, there o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyves grew: and it was a land flowing with milke and honny.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Nothing was wanting for delicate meate and drinke: as butter, milke fat lambs, rams, choyſe wheat, moſt excellent cla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ret wyne, all theſe the LORD gaue liberallie to Iſraell.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. For all this Iſraell who ſhould haue beene vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right became vnthankfull to GOD in their proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie like bruit beaſts miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enning their maiſters, they rebelled againſt their maker and redeemer.</p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:25087:15"/>16. Lyke vyle harlots they made the LORD their husband angrie, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſprituall whoore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, with ſtrange gods abhominable Idols.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. They came to the hieſt degree of idolatry: to giue the worſhip propper to GOD to devils: yea they were ſo fooliſh, that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the God whom they knew, or rather who knew them: they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped vnknowne gods, and did not follow their holy fathers footſteps.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. All this thou dideſt not of ſimple but of wilfull ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance after ſo great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of Gods loue to thee and care for thee.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. After that the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered this their apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie hee caſt off theſe that before by outward cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing appeared to bee his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. Then hee ſaid, I will miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them, I am wearie of them, there is no good to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25087:16"/>be looked for, from them, they will in end periſh miſerably.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. As they haue done to me ſo ſhal I doe to them, they forſooke mee and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed idols, <hi>I</hi> ſhall forſake them &amp; ſet other nations aboue them: yea, the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles whom they deſpyſe, I will take in their place to be my people, and caſt them off.</p>
                  <p n="22">22 <hi>I</hi> ſhall be to them a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fyre, hie nor low ſhal not eſcape my wrath, their land and all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe thereof will I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy.</p>
                  <p n="23">23 I will multiply my plagues vpon them, as arrows out of my quiver ſhotte at them.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. Namelie famine, peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, wyld beaſts &amp; Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, ſo openly and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, without and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, they ſhall bee plagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                  <p n="25">25 No ſort of perſon, no ſex: neither younge nor old
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25087:16"/>without or within, ſhall bee free from the feare and ſtroake of the ſword of the enemie.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. Whereas I had made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the ſtarres in number and glorie, I purpoſe to put them in obſcure pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and roote them out.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. If I had no reſpect to my glorie that it ſhould not be the ſubject of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of the Gentils, I ſhould vtterly haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed them.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. Their madnes is vncura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble why ſhould I ſpaire them: no counſell will they follow, neither haue they any wit.</p>
                  <p n="29">29. It is a pittie to ſee the hardneſſe of their heart, that after ſo long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of puniſhment, they cannot conſider their caſe nor what will be their end</p>
                  <p n="30">30. So long as I fought for them and was with them, no multituds could reſiſt them, now while as man
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25087:17"/>of them are overcome by few, it is evident they want my protection.</p>
                  <p n="31">31. I take to witneſſe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels who by experience of my power finde, that I am not lyke their idols.</p>
                  <p n="32">32. Moreover, they &amp; their workes are wicked, as if they had beene the ſeed of Sodom and Gomorah; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous and bitter fruit bring they foorth.</p>
                  <p n="33">33. No nation ſo wicked as they, being lyker to Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons and Aſpes nor men.</p>
                  <p n="34">34. This their wickedneſſe is laid vp in ſtore with mee, and treaſured vp in the treaſure of my wrath, againſt the day thereof, and revelation of my righteous judgement.</p>
                  <p n="35">35. I am judge of all the world, it is my office to puniſh, howbeit I ſeeme to delay, you ſhall fall in due tyme, your deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bee the evill that ſhall come vpon you at hand.</p>
                  <p n="36">36. Albeit the LORD ſhall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25087:17"/>judge his people: yet at laſt hee ſhall be appeaſed, and moved with repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to mitigate the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor of his wrath, when hee ſhall ſee all their ſtrength gone, and all al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt deſtroyed at home and abroade.</p>
                  <p n="37">37. Then ſhall they ſay to their enemies, where are your gods, where are your rocks, your particular pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons in whom ye truſted</p>
                  <p n="38">38. Before who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Prieſts did eat the fat of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and dranke the wine of their drinke offering, let thoſe idols helpe you now and take your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
                  <p n="39">39. Let them who haue eyes to ſee behold mee, and make no gods my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion: for I haue power to kill, and to keepe aliue, to wound, &amp; make heale: let them in all changes truſt in mee, and feare to offend mee, whoſe hand none can eſcape.</p>
                  <p n="40">
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:25087:18"/>40. For I hold vp my hand to Heaven and ſweare, ſaying, As I am the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>living GOD.</p>
                  <p n="41">41. My enemies thinke my ſword wil alwayes be hid in the ſcabard, and becauſe I am patient, that I ceaſe to bee a iuſt judge: but they ſhall feele the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trare, when my wrath ſhall breake out againſt them.</p>
                  <p n="42">42. There ſhall bee no end of my vengeance, vntill the earth bee filled with blood and dead bodies, &amp; my enemies be made cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, vpon whom <hi>I</hi> will haue no mercie.</p>
                  <p n="43">43. Seeing GOD will mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt his goodneſſe to his people I ſraell, &amp; his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: it is the part of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to acknowledge the ſame, and to praiſe him in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of Sancts both of Iewes &amp; Gentiles</p>
               </div>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:25087:18"/>
                  <head>The argument and analyſis of this ſong.</head>
                  <p>GOD cauſed and commanded Moſes to write this Song, &amp; preach it to Iſrael, and to teſtifie Gods goodneſſe and grace to them, and to convince them of vnthankfulneſſe towards God, and to prepare the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick kirk of the Iewes, who were to bee diſperſed through the world: Therefore hee commanded this ſong to bee put in the mouth of the Iſraelites, and to be preſerved in writen monuments. Deut 31.19. The ſumme of this Song is this: GOD the Father of his Church and Iudge of all the world, conteſts with the people of Iſrael by this ſolemne Song, of his goodneſſe towards them, of their ingratitude and contumacie ſeene already in Moſes dayes: and now forſeene by him that it would bee greater heereafter, and therefore propheſieth by Moſes of the rejection of the Iewes, &amp; calling of the Gentiles.</p>
                  <p>The parts of this ſong are three: 1. the preface, verſe 1.2.3. The 2. a narration from the 4. verſe to the 43. The 3. the concluſion of the Song. verſe 43. The 1. part which is the preface or beginning of the ſong, con taineth an exhortation to the Heavens and earth to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to this Song, verſe 1. a reaſon of this exhortation verſe 2. a precept to the people to bee attentive &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile with the reaſon thereof, verſe 3.</p>
                  <p>The 2. part of the Song containeth in it, firſt, a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of things bygone before the penning of this ſong from the 4. verſe to the 19. Secondly, a narration of things that were to come, from the 19. to the 43. The ſumme of the narration of things bygone is ſet downe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25087:19"/>verſe 4.5. The enarration or expoſition thereof from the 5. verſe to the 19. and the ſumme containeth in it 2. things: The 1. concernes God, verſe 4: The 2. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the people of Iſrael, verſe 5. which is aggredg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and they taxed with foule ingratitude, verſe 6. The enarration and expoſition of theſe thinges keepes this order. 1. the part of God is ſet downe from the 6. verſ to the 15. Next the part of the people is ſet downe: from the 15. verſe to the 19. Gods part, verſe 6, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by antiquitie and teſtimonie of their fore-beears, verſe 7. and from his providence for them from the beginning of the world, verſe 8. with the reaſon ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, verſe 9. Thirdly from his care of them when they were in the Wildernes, verſe 10. illuſtrated by ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, verſe 11.12. Fourthly, from his placing of them in the land of <hi>CANAAN,</hi> verſe 13.14. The enar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the part of the people, and the expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, verſe 16.17.18. The 2. part of the narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning things to come; containeth 2. things, 1. Gods juſtice againſt the vnthankful and rebellious Iewes, from the 19. to the 35. Secondly, the work of Gods mercy to a remnant of them from the 35 verſe to the 43. The worke of Gods juſtice is ſet downe in this order. 1. that he abhorred them, and the reaſon, verſe 19.2. that hee reſolved to leave them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, with the reaſon thereof, verſe 20.3. That hee will pay them home with like, for like; <hi>lege talionis,</hi> verſe 21. with the reaſon thereof, verſe 22. 4. That he will multiplie plagues vpon them, verſe 23.24.25. 5. That hee purpoſed to haue put away their memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial amongſt men, were not the reſpect hee had to his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25087:19"/>owne glorie, and the pride of their enemies, verſe 26, 27. 6. Hee wiſheth they had a minde and heart to conſider, and bee ſenſible of his dealings with them, &amp; of their end, together with the reaſon of all, verſe 28.29.30. which he proves by the teſtimonie of Gentils their enemies, verſe 31. and ſubjoyneth reaſons of his ſeveritie againſt them, verſe 32.33.34.35. The work of his mercy to the remnant of them is ſet down verſe 36. Amplified with the triumph and iuſulting of his people over their enemies, verſe 37.38. Which hee confirmeth by the demonſtration of his power, verſe 39. and by his oath, verſe 40.41.42. The concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Song, verſe 43. containeth an exhortation to the Church catholick of Iewes and Gentiles to praiſe God with the reaſon thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="annotations">
                  <head>Annotations vpon this Song.</head>
                  <p>Verſe. 2. <hi>My doctrine:</hi> the Hebrew word ſignifieth received learning, a good deſcription of the doctrine of true religion, becauſe it is receiued from GOD, not devyſed by men. 1. Cor. 11.23. Ioh. 8.28. and ſhould be receaved by the hearers with this reſpect. 1. Theſſ. 2.13. and this imports that the teacher receaues it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, and the hearers alſo from him by his miniſters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shall drop:</hi> ſo <hi>Micah.</hi> 5.7. Eſay. 55.10. The doctrine of falſe teachers not ſo, Iud: 6.12. Pro. 25.15. and this is a wiſh rather then a promiſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Raine. dew;</hi> figures of heavenly graces. Gen. 27.28</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Graſſe:</hi> here vnto people compared for their frailtie Eſ. 40.6. or admonition to bee fruitfull. Heb. 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:25087:20"/>Verſe 3. <hi>The name:</hi> that is his majeſtie, his workes of mercie and juſtice.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 4. <hi>ROCK:</hi> The ſeptuagints tranſlate this word: GOD who is a Rocke to his Church. Mat. 16.18. 1. Cor. 10.4 and this word imports GODS con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, wherein his ſervants truſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>His worke:</hi> The Greeke tranſlats workes. Heb. 3.9.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 5. <hi>Not of his ſonnes:</hi> for they ſinne of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie: and this ſhowes the effect of the law differing from the effect of the Ghoſpelf. Rom. 7.9. Phil. 2.5.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 6. <hi>Requyt:</hi> ſee the contrare ſpoken to God by David, Pſal. 103.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Father that bought thee:</hi> this aggredges their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe, forgetting the benefites of their redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, adoption, regeneration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Made thee:</hi> that is, not onely created thee, but alſo redeemed and called thee, and put thee in a high eſtate whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou was nothing 1. Sam. 12 6. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 43.7. Mark 3.14</p>
                  <p>Verſe 7. <hi>The dayes of old:</hi> That is, looke not ſo much what thou art now, as what thy forbears were once. Ioſ. 24. this argument alſo is vſed for conſolation. Pſ. 77.67. Pſal. 119.52. Pſal. 14.3.5.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 9. <hi>Thy Elders:</hi> who are yet living among you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Portion:</hi> that is, the Church and members thereof are the heirs of God &amp; coheirs with Chriſt. Ro. 8.17.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 10. <hi>Wilderneſſe:</hi> that is, I fand them needie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy flying fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the enemy, enemies to me, but I gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly and mercifullie receaved and intertained them though moſt vnworthie. Ezec. 16. Rom. 5.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aple of his eye:</hi> that is, with all greateſt care, alluding to mans practiſe, who will caſt vp any part of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25087:20"/>to receaue a ſtroake and ſaue the eye.</p>
                  <p>Verſ. 11. <hi>Eagle:</hi> The ſame ſimilitude is in Exod. 19 which ſheweth his fathealy care to his people, which is exponed by theſe parts, ſturring vp, to wit, by a noiſe about her birde mooving her wings to giue them wind, ſtreatching her wings for example to them to flie, taking them out of their neſt, putting them vpon her wings, that being taken from their neſt they might bee compelled to flee further: All theſe may bee ſeene in GODS dealing with his people, when hee brought them out of Egypt, ſtirring them vp by his word of promiſe mooving them with the winde of his wrath vpon Egypt, taken vnder his protection and as caried vpon wings brought them through the red ſea.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 13. <hi>Ryde vpon hie places:</hi> ſo that no ſtrength could withſtand them. Numb. 20. Deut. 2.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 14. <hi>Neares of wheat:</hi> That is the beſt, ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led becauſe of kirnels of nuts the graine is within: and for ſome reſemblance that good graines of wheat haue to neares.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The red blood:</hi> Becauſe the claret wine in Iudea is both beſt &amp; moſt aboundant as witnes <hi>Strabo</hi> &amp; <hi>Plinie</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſe 15. <hi>leſchurun:</hi> from <hi>Ieſher</hi> righteouſneſſe, or <hi>Schor,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Schor</hi> a bullok, becauſe Iſraell were by calling righteous, had a righteous law, or becauſe they ſaw the glorie of GOD in Sinai, or becauſe afterward they became a flinging bullok.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fat:</hi> The Chaldea interprets riche ſo this maxime hath ever holden true: <hi>Eccleſia peperit divitias &amp; filia devoravit matrem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſe 17. <hi>Devils:</hi> in Hebrew <hi>Schedim,</hi> that is, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:25087:21"/>of mankynd.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 19. <hi>Saw it:</hi> That is, as a righteous judge, hee tooke cognition of their wickedneſſe, and decreed to abdicat them:</p>
                  <p>Verſe. 20. <hi>I will hyde:</hi> That is, I will abdicat them and not looke vpon them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I ſhall ſee:</hi> I will giue them over to a reprobate ſenſe that they may periſh.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 21. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anities:</hi> The Septuagints cals them Idols Ier. 18.19. Ionah. 2.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Not a people:</hi> that is, the Gentils whom I will call by the preaching of the Ghoſpell. Rom. 10.19. Eſ. 65.2</p>
                  <p>Verſe 23. <hi>Arrows:</hi> All ſort of plagues as after is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned of famine (the Hebrew word not in any part of Scripture but heere) peſtilence. Hab, 3.5. wylde beaſts, ſerpents, ſword.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 36. <hi>Iudge his people:</hi> That is, take their cauſe in hand and defend them from their enemies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shall repent:</hi> So ſpeaketh the Scripture of GOD af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of man: but in ſimple trueth repentance is not in GOD: Numb. 23. 1. Sam. 15.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The hand gone:</hi> that is, their ſtrength and they nothing.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 37. <hi>Hee ſhall ſay:</hi> that is GOD to his people Ieremie. 2.28.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 39. <hi>I, I:</hi> The pronoune doubled to ſtirre vp the people to hold faſt their faith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations of grounds for vſe and doctrine.</head>
                  <p>Obſ. 1. BEcauſe GOD as a judge was to pronounce ſentence againſt his people in the ſong:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:25087:21"/>Moſes begins with a majeſticall preface, lyke vnto the ſound of a trumpet before Princes proclamations.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 2. This majeſticall preface ſerves to keepe the people in due reverence of this ſong, that neither pride mooue them to diſpyſe it, nor the ſharp threatnings contained therein, make them loath.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 3. verſ. 1. Hee directs his ſpeach to Heaven &amp; earth, taking and making them witneſſes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſtupiditie, if they condemne this doctrine: Alſo to ſhew that ſuch is the force of GODS word that all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſhould bee attentiue there vnto. Eſ. 1.2. Ier. 23. and ſo the living are ſent to the ſchoole of the dead to learne at them.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 4. The word of GOD is as dew and raine vpon graffe and herbs when it meets with good ground: but hearts hard lyke ſtones get no good thereby. Heb. 6.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 5. The Hebrew word which is exponed doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, ſignifieth properly perception or diſcipline, and teaches that the miniſters of the word ſhould deliver nothing to the people but that which haue bene taught, and receaved of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 6. verſ. 2. The word of GOD is compared to dew and raine, which ſimilitude, teacheth that the Church is Gods land or lizzure, and the word of God the food thereof making his people grow in grace.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 7. Moſes profeſſeth himſelf to bee Gods He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauld, proclaiming his praiſe, and ſo teacheth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple their duety to doe ſo.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 8. By the name of God he meaneth Gods ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties works, of goodneſſe and grace, his ſevere judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments all which he ſetteth downe after.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:25087:22"/>Obſ. 9. verſe 3. The words <hi>IEHOVAH,</hi> and <hi>our GOD</hi> imply reaſons to perſwade the practiſe of the duety craved: theſe arguments in Scripture are oft fund together: the 1. taken from Gods nature; the 2. from his covenant of grace.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 10. The conſideration of the perfection of God and of his works, as done in judgment, trueth, juſtice and righteouſnes; ſhould keepe vs from running from God to Idols. Ier. 2.13.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 11. The perfection of Gods works in creation or providence, is not to be ſought in everie particular ſo much as in the generall, ſeing amongſt beaſts there be ſome we call vnbeaſts, and amongſt men ſome croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſome blind, ſome deafe, ſome maimed and mutilat of one member or other, and all corne commeth not to perfection: yet in theſe defects God is glorified.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 12. verſe 4. The trueth of God and his fidelitie ſhould teach vs to belieue him and his word: yet his fidelitie prejudgeth not his juſtice againſt vnbelievers for hee is juſt and right.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 13. It may be mervailed that the people bore with Moſes libertie in rebuking them: yet it behoved to bridle them, that they knew this worthie ſervant of God was ſhortly to depart from this life.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 14. Hypocrits are ſometimes called Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Eſay 1.2. ſometimes they are denyed to bee the children of God, when Adoption by generall vocation is reſtrained to particulare Election.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 15. Moſes deſcribing the peoples ingratitude to God beginneth firſt at their action, in theſe words: <hi>They corrupted themſelves,</hi> that is: by their owne deed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:25087:22"/>loſt the eſtate of grace offered to them by outward cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: and caſt themſelfe in courſe of perdition. 2. hee ſets downe the blot remaining after their action: in theſe words: <hi>their spot, not the ſpot of his children:</hi> 3. hee ſets downe the habit contracted of both, calling them: a perverſe &amp; crooked generation. Theſe 3 may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in all actuall and outward ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 16. As Adam and Evah by their firſt ſinne, fell from the integritie of nature: ſo ſuch as ſeemed by out ward vocation and adoption to be in the ſtate of grace, by turning from GOD, fals from that which they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to haue.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 17. verſe 5. Sinne leaves behind it a ſpot: as diſeaſes in the lever and leproſie ſend foorth ſpots in the skinne and fleſh: This ſpot of ſinne, is a diſpoſition of the heart to bee apt and prone to the ſinne once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or to any other. This ſpot in the reprobat dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpot of Gods children, becauſe vpon the one it draweth on totall and finall apoſtaſie: vpon the other not ſo, God giving grace to repent.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 18. The more liberall God is to vs, the more thankfull ſhould wee bee: the taſte of his goodneſſe ſhould force vs to loue him.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 19. God is good to all his creatures, but in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall manner to his Church. Pſal. 147.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 20. The benefits of adoption and regeneration are attributed to hypocrites, becauſe externally they are called thereto. But they are proper to the Elect, whom <hi>Paul</hi> calleth, <hi>the worke of GOD created to good workes.</hi> Eph. 2. or <hi>Moſes</hi> heere by the word <hi>made,</hi> as in the 15. verſe meanes, <hi>Gods providence in making his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:25087:23"/>people great and renowned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Obſ. 21. verſe 6. This aggredgeth the peoples vn, thankfulneſſe, that God was ſo good to them, and they wicked againſt God.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 22. If wee will looke back to our beginning na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, ſpirituall, or civill: wee ſhall ſee wee haue no reaſon to bee proud.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 23. verſe 7. The beſt and ſureſt witneſſes of Gods benefites, are theſe, who beeing indeede godlie haue had long experience of them.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 24. God ſo loved his Church that in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world, and in the midſt of his providence, hee had a ſpeciall regard to it: not for their merite, but becauſe of his gratious election, and adoption: where by hee hath made them his heirs, and coheirs with CHRIST. Rom. 2.8. verſe. 8.9.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 25.10.11.12. David Pſ. 105. repeats GODs benefites to this people, farther of nor Moſes doeth in this ſong: for Moſes labouring to bee ſhort, beginneth at their comming to the wilderneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 26. verſe 13.14. Varietie of creatures for mans neceſſitie, vtilitie, and pleaſure, flowes from GODS li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie to man, for the which man ſhould bee thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. See Pſal. 104.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 27. verſe 15. <hi>Ieſchurun:</hi> or hee who ſhould haue beene righteous is put for Iſraell, by Ironicall il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion becauſe they prooved vnrighteous and vnthankfull: ſo GOD to Adam. Gen. 3.22.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 28. Hee concluds all the faults of this people with their ſinne of Idolatrie: the haynouſneſſe whereof hee ſets foorth by the ſimilitude of an impudent harlot
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:25087:23"/>proſtituting her ſelfe to other men, of purpoſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke her husband to anger: for idolatrie is the higheſt ſinne againſt GODS Law.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 29. Men and women are called GODs children by nature, becauſe of creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or by grace by regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, generallie, or in a ſpeciall reſpect: Moſes cals this people ſo heere, becauſe of their generall and outward calling, which divynes cals, <hi>voluntatem ſigni:</hi> &amp; diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it: <hi>a voluntate bene placiti.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Obſ. 30. GOD puniſhes not raſhlie, but takes firſt due inquiſition of the fault, howbeit he needs not who knoweth all things: by his example to teach judges their duetie. See Geneſ. 11.5. and 18.21.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 31. verſe 19. If GOD lye aback from vs and leaue vs to our ſelfe; wee ſhall runne to perdition, and if hee returne to vs wee ſhall bee ſaved. Pſal. 30, 39. &amp; Pſalme. 80.3.7.19.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 32, GOD raiſde vp the Egyptians, Syrians, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrians, Babilonians, Grecians, Romans, againſt his people: All thoſe he calleth fooliſh, how beit they were politick, honorable, wealthie: vet vnlyke to the people of GOD while they ſerved GOD. See Deut. 4.6.7.8. and Pſal. 147.19.20.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 33. It is a fearefull thing to fall in the hands of GOD beeing angrie with vs, for even our GOD is a conſuming fyre. Heb. 12.29.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 34. verſe 20.21. All plagues and puniſhments comes from God Amos. 3.6. yet to the godly they are made fatherly chaſtiſments for their good. Heb. 12</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 35. verſe 27.28. GOD magnifies his mercie in making grace to ſuperabound, where ſinne abounded
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:25087:24"/>Rom. 5.20. and his owne glorie is the end of all his working.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 36.29.30. &amp;c. GOD requyres three things of his people which hee miſſed in them. 1. The habit of wiſedome. 2. The vnderſtanding of things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his glorie and their owne ſalvation. 3. prouidence to foreſee things to come.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 37, verſe 34.35. GODS judgements ſleepe not, (as wicked men thinke) but ly at the doore Gen. 4. &amp; 7. Ier. 17.1. 2. Pet. 3.9.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 38. When GOD hath chaſtiſed his people e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neugh, hee will caſt the rod in the fire, and in wrath remember mercie, Hab. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. Pſal. 89. Pſal. 30. Eſay. 54.8. that wee may haue experience heereof, true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is requyred at our hands. Zach. 2.3.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 39. When our eſtate is moſt deſperate GODS helpe is neareſt, that hee onely may haue the praiſe. 2. King. 14.26.</p>
                  <p>Obſ 40. GOD is the ſupreme ruler of al things ordinar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or extraordinar, of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; delivera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces therefro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>Obſ. 41. verſe 36.37 &amp;c. Wee defraud GOD of his right, if wee ſet him not aboue all, and according to our place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> gifts, callings, trample not vnder foote, al Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, ſuperſtition, will worſhip, inventions and tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, which cannot bee demonſtrat by the word of GOD: whether it bee in matters of faith, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Church government, or ceremonies joyned to the worſhip of GOD.</p>
                  <p>Obſ 42 verſe 40.41.42. In holy Scripture, wee find many oaths which GOD makes, joyned ſometime to promiſes, and hee doth both promiſe and ſweare
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:25087:24"/>that by two immutable things hee may confirme our faith, Hebr. 6.18, and when hee ſweares hee ſweares by himſelfe as having none greater. ibid. 13.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 43. The whole Catholick Church of Iewes and Gentils and exhorted to ſing and praiſe the LORD, for his workes both of juſtice and mercie which hee would manifeſt to them. Rom. 15.10.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 44. The word expiation alludes to the legall ceremonies, and imports that ſalvation that was to be perfyted by IESVS CHRIST.</p>
                  <p>Obſ, 45. verſe 43 With this propheſie of the calling of the Gentils, and converſion of the Iewes, as with a blaſt of a trumpet after a Kings proclamation hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluds this ſong.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="song">
                  <head>This ſong in meeter followeth to be ſung with the tune of the <hi>78.</hi> Pſalme.</head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>Verſe. 1.</head>
                     <l>HEare O yee Heavens what I doe ſpeake,</l>
                     <l>O Earth my wordes attend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>Verſ. 2.</head>
                     <l>My doctrine ſhall drop down as raine,</l>
                     <l>my ſpeach lyke deaw I'le ſpend.</l>
                     <l>And as ſmall raine on tender hearbs,</l>
                     <l>and ſhowres vpon the graſſe</l>
                     <l>So ſhall my word much fruit bring foorth,</l>
                     <l>not beeing heard amiſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>Verſ. 3.</head>
                     <l>Since I the name of God the Lord,</l>
                     <l>will publiſh and proclame:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:25087:25"/>Aſcribe yee people all to him</l>
                     <l>the greatneſſe of the ſame:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <head>Verſ. 4.</head>
                     <l>God is a rocke, his work's perfite,</l>
                     <l>for all his wayes are juſt.</l>
                     <l>A ſtrong God, faithfull, without ſinne,</l>
                     <l>hee muſt bee right and juſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>Verſ. 5.</head>
                     <l>His people are become corrupt,</l>
                     <l>and filthie now they are,</l>
                     <l>Perverſe and crooked is their kinde,</l>
                     <l>vnlike his children deare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="6">
                     <head>Verſ. 6.</head>
                     <l>O fooliſh people and vnwiſe,</l>
                     <l>who ſo the Lord reward:</l>
                     <l>Thy Father, Maker, Saviour,</l>
                     <l>wilt thou not him regard?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="7">
                     <head>Verſ. 7.</head>
                     <l>The dayes of old, the ages paſt,</l>
                     <l>fathers, fore-beears all:</l>
                     <l>Will tell and teach thee this for treuth,</l>
                     <l>if for them thou wilt call.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="8">
                     <head>Verſ. 8.</head>
                     <l>When the moſt High to Nations,</l>
                     <l>did heritage divide:</l>
                     <l>A pleaſant bounds for Iſrael</l>
                     <l>hee did even then provide.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="9">
                     <head>Verſ. 9.</head>
                     <l>For they his choſen people were,</l>
                     <l>the portion of the Lord,</l>
                     <l>The line on them layde for himſelfe</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="10">
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:25087:25"/>
                     <head>Verſ. 10.</head>
                     <l>Hee found him in a Wilderneſſe,</l>
                     <l>was roaring, waſte, and voyde:</l>
                     <l>About the which hee cauſde them goe,</l>
                     <l>for hee them ſore annoyde.</l>
                     <l>Hee ſchool'd him there, and taught him too</l>
                     <l>by long experience:</l>
                     <l>Hee kept him as the apple of</l>
                     <l>his eye with patience.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="11">
                     <head>Verſ. 11.</head>
                     <l>As Eagles flighter ov'r their young,</l>
                     <l>and ſtirres vp all their neſt:</l>
                     <l>Spreads out their wings to beare their birds,</l>
                     <l>where they themſelves think beſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="12">
                     <head>Verſ. 12.</head>
                     <l>Ev'n ſo the Lord his people led,</l>
                     <l>and with him their was none,</l>
                     <l>No ſtrange ſtrong God made any help,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>IEHOVE</hi> did all alone.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="13">
                     <head>Verſ 13.</head>
                     <l>Above the monts he cauſde them ryde</l>
                     <l>and feede in fruitfull field.</l>
                     <l>Honey from rockes, and oyle from flint,</l>
                     <l>to ſuck gaue God their ſhield.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="14">
                     <head>Verſ. 14.</head>
                     <l>Butter of kyne, and milke of ſheepe,</l>
                     <l>with fat of lambes, rammes ſweet,</l>
                     <l>Well fed on Baſhan hill they eate:</l>
                     <l>ſuch meate for them was meete.</l>
                     <l>The choiſeſt wheat, the fineſt flowre</l>
                     <l>was alſo to them foode:</l>
                     <l>The berrie of the wyne they drinke,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="15">
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:25087:26"/>
                     <head>Verſ. 15.</head>
                     <l>But Iſrael grew fat and flang,</l>
                     <l>both fat and groſſe grew thou:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ieſchurun</hi> vpright ſhould haue beene,</l>
                     <l>though fat him covered thorow.</l>
                     <l>His God who made him hee forſakes,</l>
                     <l>and ſo Salvation.</l>
                     <l>Him hee deſpiſed who did him good,</l>
                     <l>ſo vngrate's this Nation.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="16">
                     <head>Verſ. 16.</head>
                     <l>To jealouſie with their ſtrange gods,</l>
                     <l>then did they him provoke:</l>
                     <l>To anger with thinges hee abhorr'd,</l>
                     <l>caſting from them his yoke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="17">
                     <head>Verſ. 17.</head>
                     <l>To Devils they did ſacrifice</l>
                     <l>in place of God their Lord:</l>
                     <l>The gods both new and neare they ſerv'de,</l>
                     <l>their fathers ſuch abhorr'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="18">
                     <head>Verſ. 18.</head>
                     <l>The Rocke begate thee thou forgate</l>
                     <l>the God that brought thee out</l>
                     <l>Of mothers wombe: is out of mind,</l>
                     <l>hee'le puniſh thee but doubt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="19">
                     <head>Verſ. 19.</head>
                     <l>For when the Lord ſaw all their ſins,</l>
                     <l>hee abdicat with griefe</l>
                     <l>His ſonnes, and eeke his daughters all,</l>
                     <l>and made them no reliefe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="20">
                     <head>Verſ. 20.</head>
                     <l>And then hee ſaid. my face from them</l>
                     <l>heereafter I will hyde:</l>
                     <l>And I will ſee what end will bee,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:25087:26"/>A froward generation,</l>
                     <l>vnfaithfull children they</l>
                     <l>Are now become: and will no more</l>
                     <l>My holy Law obey.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="21">
                     <head>Verſe 21.</head>
                     <l>To jealouſie with their none gods,</l>
                     <l>ſince they doe mee provoke,</l>
                     <l>And with their vanities trouble mee.</l>
                     <l>how beit they bee my flocke.</l>
                     <l>With thoſe that now no people are</l>
                     <l>provoked ſhall they bee,</l>
                     <l>And with a fooliſh nation,</l>
                     <l>To rage and jealouſie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="22">
                     <head>Verſe 22.</head>
                     <l>For in my wrath there kindled is.</l>
                     <l>a hote conſuming fire:</l>
                     <l>Which ſhall burne downe vnto the deepe,</l>
                     <l>Through earth, through dub, through myre,</l>
                     <l>There ſhall bee left no fruit on earth,</l>
                     <l>increaſe there ſhall bee none,</l>
                     <l>The grounds of mountaines great alſo,</l>
                     <l>this fire ſhall burne vpon.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="23">
                     <head>Verſe 23.</head>
                     <l>My plagues on them I'le multiplie,</l>
                     <l>And ſpend my arrows all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="24">
                     <head>Verſe 24.</head>
                     <l>Brunt vp with hunger ſhall they bee,</l>
                     <l>with peſt lyke burning coale:</l>
                     <l>Bitter deſtruction will I ſend,</l>
                     <l>by beaſts devoruing luſt,</l>
                     <l>And ſerpents poyſon ſhall them hurt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="25">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:25087:27"/>
                     <head>Verſe 25.</head>
                     <l>Without the ſword ſhall orphans make</l>
                     <l>within all full of feare:</l>
                     <l>The choſen youth, the virgin cloſe,</l>
                     <l>the infant and gray haire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="26">
                     <head>Verſe 26.</head>
                     <l>I ſaid that I ſhould ſcatter them,</l>
                     <l>in corners: and ſhould make</l>
                     <l>Of them no more memoriall,</l>
                     <l>that one might notice take.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="27">
                     <head>Verſe 27.</head>
                     <l>Were not I feare the wrath of thoſe</l>
                     <l>that enemies were to mee,</l>
                     <l>Leaſt they ſhould ſay through ignorance,</l>
                     <l>God did not this but wee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="28">
                     <head>Verſe 28.</head>
                     <l>A nation voyde of counſell they,</l>
                     <l>yet counſell will not take:</l>
                     <l>In them no vnderſtanding is,</l>
                     <l>I ſorrow for their ſake.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="29">
                     <head>Verſe 29.</head>
                     <l>Oh that they ſomuch wiſdome had</l>
                     <l>as this to vnderſtand,</l>
                     <l>Their latter end what it will bee,</l>
                     <l>who ſuch things take in hand.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="30">
                     <head>Verſe. 30.</head>
                     <l>How ſhould it come to paſſe that one</l>
                     <l>a thouſand men ſhould chaſe,</l>
                     <l>Or two ten thouſand ſhould compell,</l>
                     <l>To flee before their face?</l>
                     <l>If not becauſe their rocke ſo ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>had ſold them for no pryce,</l>
                     <l>And GOD had cauſd them yeeld themſelfe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="31">
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:25087:27"/>
                     <head>Verſe 31.</head>
                     <l>Your enemies judges if yee make,</l>
                     <l>their god is not like yours:</l>
                     <l>So ſtrong a Rocke to truſt vnto,</l>
                     <l>all yeares, and dayes, and howrs.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="32">
                     <head>Verſe 32.</head>
                     <l>Of Sodoms ground &amp; Gomors field</l>
                     <l>their vine with venmous graps,</l>
                     <l>And bitter are their cluſters all,</l>
                     <l>when they are laid on heaps.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="33">
                     <head>Verſe 33.</head>
                     <l>And ſo the wine that thereof comes,</l>
                     <l>like Dragons venome kils,</l>
                     <l>Or like the cruell head of Aſpes,</l>
                     <l>whom poyſon fully fils.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="34">
                     <head>Verſe 34.</head>
                     <l>Doe I not keepe this ſure in ſtore,</l>
                     <l>My treaſures ſeald among,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="35">
                     <head>Verſe 35.</head>
                     <l>Vengeance is mine I will repay,</l>
                     <l>For I am GOD the ſtrong.</l>
                     <l>Their foote ſhall ſlyde betyme, For why?</l>
                     <l>the day'f perdition,</l>
                     <l>Is neare: and bring with it in haſte,</l>
                     <l>to them confuſion.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="36">
                     <head>Verſe 36.</head>
                     <l>The Lord ſhall judge his people ſo,</l>
                     <l>and yet hee ſhall repent</l>
                     <l>When hee ſhall ſee his ſervants ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>that all their ſtrength is ſpent,</l>
                     <l>And few or none left to remaine.</l>
                     <l>in citie or in field,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="37">
                     <head>Verſe 37,</head>
                     <l>Then ſhall they ſay their foes to ſcorne</l>
                     <l>where is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="38">
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:25087:28"/>
                     <head>Verſ. 38.</head>
                     <l>Where are your gods who eat the fat,</l>
                     <l>Of offerings, and dranke wyne,</l>
                     <l>Let thoſe rvſe vp and helpe you now,</l>
                     <l>or flee from mee and myne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="39">
                     <head>Verſe 39.</head>
                     <l>See now that I, even I alone,</l>
                     <l>no other gods with mee:</l>
                     <l>I kill, and I giue life alſo,</l>
                     <l>I wound and I heale thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="40">
                     <head>Verſe 40.</head>
                     <l>And none can put out of my hand.</l>
                     <l>which vp to heaven I lift,</l>
                     <l>And ſay, As I for ever liue,</l>
                     <l>the enemie ſhall not ſhift.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="41">
                     <head>Verſe 41.</head>
                     <l>When I my gliſtring ſword ſhal ſharp,</l>
                     <l>to judgement lay my hand:</l>
                     <l>Then on my foes Ile bee avengd,</l>
                     <l>my haters ſhall not ſtand.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="42">
                     <head>Verſe 42.</head>
                     <l>My arrows ſhall be drunke with blud</l>
                     <l>My ſword ſhall fleſh devoure,</l>
                     <l>The blood ſhall bee, of men are ſlaine,</l>
                     <l>and captives more and more.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="43">
                     <head>Verſ. 43.</head>
                     <l>Praiſe yee his people, nations all</l>
                     <l>whoſe blood hee will revenge</l>
                     <l>Vpon their foes: but from his land,</l>
                     <l>and choſen will not change.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:25087:28"/>
               <head>The Song of DEBORAH. Iugdes. <hi>5.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>Text.</head>
                  <p>BEcauſe hee hath taken revenge by Iſrael, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people offered themſelfe willingly: Bleſſe yee IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH.</p>
                  <p>Heare O yee Kings, giue eare O Princes: I even I will ſing to IEHOVAH the God of Iſraell.</p>
                  <p>IEHOVAH when thou went out of Seir, when thou marched out of the land of Edom: the earth was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, alſo the Heavens drop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped, alſo the clouds dropped water.</p>
                  <p>The mountaines flowed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the face of IEHOVA:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:25087:29"/>This Sinai before the face of the GOD of Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>In the dayes of Sangar the ſonne of Anach: In the days of Iahel the hy way ceaſed: and they that walked, went by byrods and boutgates.</p>
                  <p>The villages ceaſed in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael; they ceaſed: vntill I Deborah aroſe, that I aroſe a mother in Iſraell.</p>
                  <p>When he chooſed new gods, warre was in the gates: no ſword nor ſpeare was ſene among fourtie thouſand in Iſraell.</p>
                  <p>My heart is to the law givers in Iſraell: The wel-willing among the people; Bleſſe yee IEHOVAH. Ye that ryde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whyt aſſes, ye that ſit in iudgement, ye that walke in the wayes, Speake.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:25087:29"/>The delivered from the voyce of the archers, in the places where water is drawne: there they ſhall teach the righteouſneſſe of IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH: his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe vpon his villages: then the people of Iehovah went downe to the gates.</p>
                  <p>Ryſe vp, ryſe vp Deborah, ryſe vp, ryſe vp, vtter thy ſong: Aryſe Barak &amp; lead captiue thy captivitie, thou ſonne of Abinoam.</p>
                  <p>Then hee that remained, ruled over the nobles of the people: IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH ſhall beare rule to mee among the ſtrong.</p>
                  <p>Out of Ephraim whoſe root streatches to Amalek, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Beniamin among thy people: out of Machir they came downe, and out of Zebulon, they that draw with the rod of the writer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:25087:30"/>And the Princes of Iſachar with Deborah: and Iſachar with Barak, ſent downe to the valley vpon his feete. for the diviſions of Reuben great thoughts of heart.</p>
                  <p>Why ſate thou betwixt two folds to heare the bleeting of the flocks? for the diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Reuben great ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of heart,</p>
                  <p>Gilead dwelt ſtill in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſyde Iordan: and why dwelt Dan in ſhips: Aſher ſat at the ſea ſhore &amp; dwelt vpon his Creeks.</p>
                  <p>Zebulon &amp; Naphtali were the people, who did hazard their ſoule to die vpon the places of the field.</p>
                  <p>The Kings came then they fought, the Kings of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan fought in Taanah at
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:25087:30"/>the waters of Megiddo, their deſire of ſilver they got not.</p>
                  <p>The ſtarres faught from the Heavens out of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees fought they with Siſera.</p>
                  <p>The river Kiſon ſwept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away: that ancient river Kiſon. My ſoule ſhall trample vpon the ſtrong. Then were the horſehoofes bruiſed, by the strokes of the strong.</p>
                  <p>Curſe ye Meroz ſaid the Angell of IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH: Curſing curſe yee the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants thereof: becauſe they came not to helpe! IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH, to helpe IEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH among the strong.</p>
                  <p>Iahel the wife of Cheber the Kenite ſhall bee bleſſed aboue women, aboue wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in tent ſhe ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:25087:31"/>Hee asked water and ſhee gaue him milke, ſhe broght him butter in a diſh for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</p>
                  <p>Her hand ſent themſelves to the naile: and her right hand to the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer of worke men: and ſhee hammered Siſera, ſhe cut off his head: ſhee pricked through, and pearſed the temple of his head.</p>
                  <p>Betwixt her feete hee was bowed together, hee fell, hee ſleept betwixt her feet: hee bowed himſelfe, hee fell where hee bowed himſelfe, there hee fell spoyled.</p>
                  <p>The mother of Siſera looked through the window, and cryed out at the open of the window, Why tarryes his charet from comming? why are the turning of his foure wheeles made ſlow.</p>
                  <p>Her wiſe ladies anſwered vnto her, alſo ſhee her ſelfe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:25087:31"/>turned her speaches to her ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Haue they not found? ſhall they not divyde the spoyle? one damoſell, two damoſels, for everie man: The spoyle of colours for Siſera him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the ſpoyle of party col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of needle worke, two of spoyle for the necke.</p>
                  <p>So let thy enemies all pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh IEHOVAH: and let thoſe that loue him, bee as the ſunne going foorth in his strength.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="paraphrase">
                  <pb facs="tcp:25087:28"/>
                  <head>Paraphraſe.</head>
                  <p>PRaiſe yee the LORD who both hath made you able to revenge your ſelfe vpon your enemies, and given you courage to fight, and power to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. O yee Kings who truſt in your might, &amp; rulers who lift vp your ſelfe in pryde: heare and hearken vnto the words of this ſong; wherein the LORD, the GOD of Iſrael is praiſed: for it ſerveth to teach you.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 O LORD when thou led thy people from mount Seir, and the land of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom toward the land of Canaan: all creatures in Heaven and earth were moved with thy preſence among thy people.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Yea the mountaines that ſeemd ſo ſolid melted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:25087:29"/>the face of the LORD, even mount Sinai where thou gaue thy law.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. A long time before this our laſt deliverance our eſtate was ſo hard, that from the death of Ehud vnto this tyme: none durſt goe abroad, for feare of the enemie.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. And as the people durſt not travell in hie wayes: So might they not abyde in villages: vntill the time that GOD raiſed mee vp, to foretell and confirme the deliverance of his peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Becauſe Iſrael choſed new gods, God raiſed vp new enemies to ſight againſt them and oppreſſe them: ſo that no weapon was found among them.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. I rejoyce of the Princes of Iſrael and of the people who came willingly to battell. Bleſſe ye the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 Let al ſort of people ſpeak of this work of God: but namely merchants, judges,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:25087:29"/>way-faring folke, where before hid them ſelues for feare of the enemie.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Before for feare of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy they durſt not come foorth to draw water, nor inhabit villages, nor miniſter juſtice: now the caſe is altered, by the righteous acts of the LORD: which wee ſhould proclaime.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Thou Deborah a prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſſe ryſe vp and ſing thy ſong of praiſe to GOD. and thou Barak captaine of the Lords armie, triumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Cananite.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. When wee were left few in number and diſpyſed: our enemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s were manie and mightie: yet the Lord hath made vs rule over the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">13. To this battel came ſome of the tribe of Ephraim, &amp; of Beniamin, and of the familie of Machir of the tribe of Manaſſeh, &amp; of the tribe of Zebulon, men more wiſe &amp; learned then valourous warriours.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:25087:30"/>14. The Princes of Iſachar were alſo with Deborah: And Iſachars ſouldiers be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing footemen; attended Barak in the valley: It greived vs much that the Reubenites concurred not to helpe vs.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Why had thou greater pleaſure in the care of thy flocks, nor in the care of the commonwealth? more care of thy beaſts then of GODS people, wee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veled much when we ſaw Reuben abſent.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Gilead came not: Dan for feare keept the boats of Iordan to flee away. Aſher alſo did ſtay at home in his ſureſt places for refuge.</p>
                  <p n="17">17 Such courage &amp; zeale was in the tribs of Zebulon &amp; Naphtali, who being few in number in compariſon with their enemies, did venter.</p>
                  <p n="18">18 Many Kings of Canaan ſent their forces with Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſera, who fought in the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:25087:30"/>plaine betwixt Taanah &amp; Megiddo: They looked for greater ſpoyle &amp; rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, but brought none away</p>
                  <p n="19">19. GOD ſhew himſelfe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie againſt the enemies of his people: and cauſed the ſtarres in their ſtations fight againſt them.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. Hee alſo cauſed the river Kiſon to ſwell &amp; drowne them: and made his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtout to ſlay them.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. So ſore were the horſe put at in fighting and flee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they being ſtrong and beating the ground. with their feete, brake all their hoofes.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. Barak the Lords meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, had good cauſe to curſe, and bide curſe the inhabitants of Meroz, who would not come foorth to helpe GODS people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo neare them.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. Iahel the wife of Cheber the Kenite ſhall bee much praiſed aboue other wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who dwell in tents.</p>
                  <p n="24">
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:25087:31"/>24. When Siſera fled &amp; came to her tent to hyde him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hee called for water to quench his thirſt: ſhee gaue him milke and butter in pretious veſſels like a freind or ſervant.</p>
                  <p n="25">25. But when ſhee ſaw him faſt a ſleepe ſhee tooke one of the nailes of the tent, with a hammer in her right hand, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe drove the naile, throgh the temples of his head faſt in the ground.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. So that hee lay firſt ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, next dead among her feete: notwithſtanding all his ſtrugling in the agony of death: So ended this great Captaine oppreſſor of others.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. Siſera his mother looking for his returne with vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, being impatient, whiles looked out at the window, whiles cryed out, why ſtayes he ſo long what can bee his ſtay.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. Her ladies eſſayed al their wits to comfort her, yea
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:25087:31"/>even ſhee comforted her ſelf with his owne words ſaying.</p>
                  <p n="29">29. They haue found their prey, they are parting the ſpoyle, even damoſels to everie man: and the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured &amp; partie coloured garments ſowed with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle worke made to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments for their neckes.</p>
                  <p n="30">30. This may bee a docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all ages, that all the enemies of GOD ſhall periſh: and thoſe that loue him ſhall ſhine as the ſun at noone day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <head>The argument and analyſis of this ſong.</head>
                  <p>AFter the death of Ehud who ſlew Eglon king of Moab, and delyvered Iſrael out of the hands of Moabits: whom they had ſerved eighteene yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Iſrael had reſt from enemies for the ſpace of foure ſcore yeares: But againe Iſrael wrought wickedneſſe in the ſight of the LORD: therefore he delivered them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver into the hands of Iabin king of the Canaanits: the generall of whoſe armie was called Siſera, who oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Iſrael the ſpace of twentie yeares: Then Iſrael re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented them of their ſinnes, humbled themſelfe and cryed to the Lord and hee heard them: And <hi>Deborah<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:25087:32"/>Barak,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iabel,</hi> he made inſtruments to deliver them. This deliverance is the argument of this Song ſung by <hi>Deborah</hi> a Propheteſſe.</p>
                  <p>There bee three chiefe and principall parts of this ſong. 1 The exordium or beginning of this ſong. verſ. 1. 2. Next the purpoſe, from the 3. verſe to the 30. Thirdly, the concluſion of the ſong. verſe 30.</p>
                  <p>The exordium containes in it 2. exhortations with their reaſons. The 1. exhortation is to Gods people to praiſe God, the reaſon thereof is taken from their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent deliverie. verſe 1. The 2 exhortation is to al kings and princes to bee attentiue to the words of this Song. The reaſon thereof is taken from the purpoſe of the Propheteſſe in this ſong, to wit, to praiſe and make manifeſt the onely true God: v. 2. ſee the like Pſ. 2. The purpoſe of the ſong containes in it chiefely 5. things: 1. a narration of things bygone, from the 3 verſe to the 8. Next an exhortation to praiſe God, from the 8. verſ to the 13. Thirdly, a narration of the battell betwixt the Iſraelites and Cananits. from the 13. to the 22. Fourthly a curſe and bleſſing, from the 22. verſe to the 27. Fifthly, a prettie proſopopeia, from the 27. verſe to the 30. The narration of things bygone, containes 2. things, 1. Gods wonderfull power in bringing his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple through the wilderneſſe, to the land of promiſe ver. 3.4. Next the great miſerie wherein Iſrael was of late: with the reaſon thereof, verſe 13. that they had ſerved new gods, idols. 5.6.7. The exhortation to praiſe God hath in it 4. things. 1. the governours of this people verſe 8. Next to merchants, verſe 9. Third to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, verſe 10. the reaſon thereof, is their libertie: The
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:25087:32"/>fourth part is to her ſelfe and Barak. verſe 11. with the reaſon thereof, verſe 12. The narration of the battell containes in it: 1. the praiſe of the tribes of Iſraell who came to fight, and the diſpraiſe of ſuch as lay abacke, from the 13. verſe to the 18. Secondly is ſet downe the part of the Canaanites. verſe 18. Thirdly the part of God and his people. verſe 19.20.21. The curſe is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Meroz and his inhabitants, with the reaſon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, verſe 22. The bleſſing is vpon Iahel, with a narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on of her part and the event thereof, from the 22. ver. to the 27 the proſopopeia is of Siſera his mother &amp; her ladies talking to gether, from the 27. verſe to the 30. The concluſion which is the laſt part of the ſong: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines a prayer for the confuſion of the enemies of God and of his Church: and for the proſperitie of all thoſe who truely loue GOD: verſe 30.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="annotations">
                  <head>Annotations vpon this ſong.</head>
                  <p>IT was the cuſtome of <hi>Lyrick</hi> Poets in giving of thanks to GOD, to vſe ſolemne verſes: as wee may read in <hi>Orpheus, Linus, Pindarus, Horace:</hi> ſo the prieſts of <hi>Mars</hi> among the Romans called <hi>Salij:</hi> All theſe did ſo by the light of nature: but holy men and women did the lyke by the inſpiration of the holy ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 1. <hi>Revenge:</hi> In Hebrew in revenging revenges</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Willing:</hi> That is, not all Iſraell but ſuch onely as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Barak who at the time had no authority in Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 2. <hi>The earth &amp;c.</hi> Hyperbolicall ſpeaches ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying the power of Gods preſence working in all his creatures.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:25087:33"/>Verſe 4. <hi>Sinai:</hi> That is to ſay, not onely creatures which were as it were before GOD in his preſence: but alſo ſuch as it were behind him were mooved.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 6. <hi>Mother:</hi> ſo called becauſe beeing endued with the ſpirit of prophecie as a mother to her childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo prophets were called fathers, their diſciples their ſonnes.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 7. <hi>Gates:</hi> or ports, ſignifying that the enemie was maſter of all, for in the ports of cities judges ſat: and the munition of the citie lay there.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 9. <hi>Whyte aſſes:</hi> This may bee exponed either of merchants or great men: as after chap. 10.4, &amp; 12.14 Verſ. 13. <hi>EPHRAIM:</hi> It may be meant of <hi>Deborah,</hi> for chap. 4.5. it is ſaid ſhe dwelt in mount Ephraim.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 14. <hi>A diſh:</hi> that is to ſay, aboundantlie, for the Hebrew word ſignifieth a veſhell cup like, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be vſed at great ſacrifices, as chap. 6.38.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Butter;</hi> That is to ſay, new milk new ſevered from the butter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations of grounds for vſe and doctrine.</head>
                  <p>Obſ. 1. <hi>DEBORAH</hi> conceived and ſung this Song by a prophetick ſpirit the very daye when the benefite was gotten: teaching vs heereby to giue thankes to God for his benefites without delaye: not lingering with Iacob to go to Bethel and performe his vowes: neither beeing vnthankfull altogether, as the nyne le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers were to Chriſt. The Ethnicks ſung their Paeans immediatly after victorie over their enemies.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 2. It is God who revengeth the wrongs done
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:25087:33"/>to his ſervants: for it is his office, Deut. 32. which when we find we ſhould praiſe him: Pſal. 18.47. nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould wee avenge our ſelf. Pro. 25.21. Ro. 12.10. Obſ. 3. v. 1. All true fortitude comes of God, and is his gift, as the right vſe of it, and good event: Pſal. 18 for our actions are not in our power: Ier. 10.23. This doctrine refuteth the errour of mans free-will.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 4. Whatſoever is writen in holy Scripture ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not only for the age when it was written, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the poſteritie: Rom. 15.4. 1. Cor. 10.11.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 5. Kings, Princes and potentates haue neede to bee exhorted to marke the judgements of God vpon their Peeres, for pride ſo blinds their mindes, that they miſ-ken both God &amp; man. Pſ. 2.10. Pſ. 70.12 Pſ. 82.6.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 6. Wee ſhould remember Gods works of olde, that wee may praiſe him, truſt in him, and be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the day of trouble. Pſal. 77.11.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 7. verſ. 3.4 All creatures in heaven &amp; earth ſerve God: only the Devils and mankind are rebellious.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 8. Peace is a great benefite of God to Church &amp; common-wealth: and Warre a great plague, therefore we ſhould pray for it. Pſal. 122.6. 1. Tim. 2.2. and praiſe God for it.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 9. verſ. 5.6. Princes and Princeſſes ſhould be nouriſhers of the Church of God. Eſay. 49.23. parents to their ſubjects, therefore even the Ethnickes by the the light of nature called them <hi>Patres patriae:</hi> and their kinſ-fold <hi>patritios.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Obſ. 10. verſ. 7. God is a jealous God, and will not ſuffer his honour to be given to another, but puniſheth Idolaters with new puniſhments, whatſoever the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:25087:34"/>bee, and howſoever mans ingine laboureth to collour or defend it.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 11. verſ. 8 9.10. Wee ſhould bee feeling mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, rejoyſing when they rejoyce, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when they mourne. Rom. 12.15. provoking o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to ſerve God. Pſal. 51.13.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 12. There are none ſo eminent in the Church who have not neede to bee ſtirred vp to their dueties. Heb. 10 24. 2. Tim. 1.6.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 13. To triumph over enemies, overcoming in lawfull warre is lawfull: all triumphs amongſt Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple before Chriſts death were but praeludes and types of Chriſts triumph vpon the Croſſe over principaliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and powers. Col. 2.15. and of his members at the latter day. 1. Cor. 2.3.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 14 verſ. 11. <hi>Deborah</hi> hath the Song named af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her, <hi>Barak</hi> the triumph after him: ſhee was the Propheteſſe, hee the leader of the Armie. Iuſtice gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to everie one his owne.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 15. verſe 13.14. By ſinne Gods people are made the taile, by repentance and obedience they become the head againe. Deut. 28.12.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 16. As their names who have beene zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the cauſe of God, and of their countrie are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrated for their everlaſting good memorie: ſo ſuch, as by infidelitie or feare haue lyen aback are noted with ſhame. Prov. 10.7.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 17. verſ. 15.16.17. <hi>Reuben</hi> the father of that tribe regarded more his pleaſure than his honour, and ſo was degraduat by his father Iacob. Gen. 49.3. This ſticks to his poſterity now, ſo ſome ſins are hereditary</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:25087:34"/>Obſ. 18. verſe. 18 Man proponeth and God diſponeth: yea, Princes haue no power to performe all their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions. Pſal. 146.4. Prov. 21.1.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 19. verſe 19.20. All creatures as at GODS command to fight againſt his enemies, &amp; the enemies of his ſervants, therefore hee is called the LORD of Hoſtes: Devils and wicked men diſobey, the one hee holds in chaines. Iud. 6. and hee can put his hooke in the noſthirles of the other. Eſ. 37.29.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 20. verſe 21. Man ſhould put his truſt in GOD onely, and in none other. Pſal. 20.7. Pſalme. 146.3.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 21. verſe 22. Whatſoever is done to Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants be it good or evill, God thinkes it done to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Mat. 25.25. Acts. 9.4.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 22 Before wee curſe or vſe imprecations, wee ſhould trye by what ſpirit wee are led, as Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Iames.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God can overthrow mightie champions by weake meane and inſtruments, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his overthrow, <hi>Siſera's<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and many moe prove.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 23. <hi>Deborah</hi> a true Propheteſſe, as the event de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared: the beſt tryall of propheſies are by event.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 24. verſe 23.24 25.26. Through faith the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were renowmed: <hi>Barak</hi> becauſe his faith was weake had little honour in his victorie, ſo <hi>Zachariah</hi> chaſtiſed for infiidelitie, Chriſts diſciples oft rebuked.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 25. verſe 27.28.29. When the wicked crye peace, peace, then ſuddenly commeth their deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 1. Theſſ. 3.3. The hope of the wicked ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, &amp; the thing they feare ſhall come vpon them.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 26. verſe 30. The petitions of Gods ſervants
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:25087:35"/>moved by his holy Spirit regiſtrated in holy Scripture are equivalent to promiſes: and beeing turned in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions comfort the godly, &amp; may affray the wicked: howbeit the Lord hold his Church vnder the croſſe for a while, yet their outgate ſhall be comfortable, &amp; their end peace. Pſ. 37.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="song">
                  <head>This ſong paraphraſed in Engliſh meeter to the tune of the <hi>76.</hi> Pſalme.</head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>Verſe. 1.</head>
                     <l>THE LORD our quarrell hath revengd,</l>
                     <l>And made our people willing fight:</l>
                     <l>Now our eſtate is meekle changd,</l>
                     <l>To bleſſe his Name wee haue good right.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>Verſ. 2.</head>
                     <l>Heare O yee Kings and Princes all,</l>
                     <l>For to IEHOVAH ſing I ſhall,</l>
                     <l>To Iaakobs GOD, the GOD of might.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>Verſ. 3.</head>
                     <l>When thou O Lord from Seir went out</l>
                     <l>And marched foorth from Edoms land,</l>
                     <l>The earth, the clowds the Sphears about,</l>
                     <l>Were moved all at thy command,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <head>Verſ. 4.</head>
                     <l>The mountaines fled before thy face,</l>
                     <l>The mount Sinai ſhooke for a ſpace,</l>
                     <l>Of Iſraels GOD they felt the hand.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>Verſ. 5.</head>
                     <l>When Sangar yet was in this life,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe father Anach was by name,</l>
                     <l>And Iahel alſo Chebers wife<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:25087:35"/>Iſrael did ſuſtaine great ſhame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="6">
                     <head>Verſ. 6.</head>
                     <l>For all their wayes were ſtopt about,</l>
                     <l>Till I Deborah did ſtep out,</l>
                     <l>Iſrael thraldome from to clame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="7">
                     <head>Verſe 7.</head>
                     <l>Iſrael to them new gods did chuſe,</l>
                     <l>And warres were made within their ports,</l>
                     <l>When they their GOD did then refuſe,</l>
                     <l>No ſpeare nor ſhield had their cohorts.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="8">
                     <head>Verſ. 8.</head>
                     <l>I loved then the nobles all,</l>
                     <l>That helped Iſrael in this thrall.</l>
                     <l>Bleſſe yee the LORD who vs comforts.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="9">
                     <head>Verſ. 9.</head>
                     <l>Merchants whyte aſſes on, who ryde,</l>
                     <l>And yee in judgement who doe ſit,</l>
                     <l>You who doe travell time and tyde,</l>
                     <l>Keepe not ſilence: but ſpeake of it.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="10">
                     <head>Verſe 10.</head>
                     <l>For feare ſuch as no water drew,</l>
                     <l>GODS juſtice foorth now they doe ſhew,</l>
                     <l>No juſtice now will judge omit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="11">
                     <head>Verſ. 11.</head>
                     <l>Ryſe vp ryſe vp againe vp ryſe,</l>
                     <l>Thou <hi>Deborah</hi> thy ſong to ſing,</l>
                     <l>And thou <hi>Barak</hi> alſo aryſe,</l>
                     <l>With thy triumph make earth to ring.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="12">
                     <head>Verſ. 12.</head>
                     <l>Lately vile ſlaves our nobles ſerv'd,</l>
                     <l>Now we doe reigne and they are ſtarv'd,</l>
                     <l>Should wee not then praiſe GOD our King?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="13">
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:25087:36"/>
                     <head>Verſ 13.</head>
                     <l>Ephram that pleaſant mightie tree,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe roote to Amalek doth reach,</l>
                     <l>Did then ſend foorth ſtrong boughs with mee,</l>
                     <l>Which Benjamin did alſo teach.</l>
                     <l>And Machir then, for to come downe,</l>
                     <l>With the ſtrong men of Zebulon:</l>
                     <l>Faire writers all and good in ſpeach.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="14">
                     <head>Verſ. 14.</head>
                     <l>With Deborah the princes were,</l>
                     <l>Of Iſachar as Barak chiefe:</l>
                     <l>With whom were many foote-men there,</l>
                     <l>Reuben, Alas made no reliefe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="15">
                     <head>Verſ. 15.</head>
                     <l>Then did yee ſit as ſtill as ſtockes,</l>
                     <l>To heare the bleating of your flockes,</l>
                     <l>And came not foorth to chaſe the thiefe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="16">
                     <head>Verſe 16.</head>
                     <l>Gilead beyond the river bode,</l>
                     <l>Then Dan with boats did ſtill remaine,</l>
                     <l>Aſcher like to a wylie Tod,</l>
                     <l>Sat at the ſea next to the plaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="17">
                     <head>Verſe 17.</head>
                     <l>But Zebulon and Napthali,</l>
                     <l>Hazard their ſoules though they ſhould die,</l>
                     <l>Vpon the mountaines of the maine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="18">
                     <head>Verſe 18.</head>
                     <l>The kings came foorth to fight that day</l>
                     <l>Even Canaans kings in Tanah field,</l>
                     <l>Megiddo's waters neare I ſay,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:25087:36"/>No profit did their labour yeild.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="19">
                     <head>Verſe 19.</head>
                     <l>For ſtarres from Heaven againſt them fought</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="20">
                     <head>Verſ. 20.</head>
                     <l>And Kiſons flud againſt them wroght</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="21">
                     <head>Ver. 21.</head>
                     <l>I tramp the ſtrong horſehoofes in field</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="22">
                     <head>Verſe 22.</head>
                     <l>Gods Angell ſaid Meroz bee curſt,</l>
                     <l>Curſe bitterly her people all.</l>
                     <l>To helpe the LORD that day, who durſt</l>
                     <l>Not come among men ſtrong and tall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="23">
                     <head>Verſe. 23.</head>
                     <l>Bleſſed bee Iahel Chebers wife,</l>
                     <l>Aboue the women all her life,</l>
                     <l>Dwelling in tents which wee doe call.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="24">
                     <head>Verſe 24.</head>
                     <l>Water hee ask'd, ſhee gaue him milk,</l>
                     <l>And butter in a lordly plate.</l>
                     <l>Betwixt her hands as ſoft as ſilke,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="25">
                     <head>Verſe 25.</head>
                     <l>Vnto a hammer made by art,</l>
                     <l>Shee put her right hand, and a naile</l>
                     <l>In her left hand, leaſt ſhee ſhould faile,</l>
                     <l>And through his temples cauſd it ſtart,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="26">
                     <head>Verſe 26.</head>
                     <l>Betwixt her feete hee bowed ſore,</l>
                     <l>Hee fell, hee ſleept betwixt her feete,</l>
                     <l>Vntill in him was life no more,</l>
                     <l>And ſo to die for him was meete.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="27">
                     <head>Verſe 27.</head>
                     <l>When his mother did then looke out</l>
                     <l>To ſpye the fields round about,</l>
                     <l>Shee ſaid, my ſonne ſtayes long in ſtreete.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="28">
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:25087:37"/>
                     <head>Verſe 28.</head>
                     <l>Her ladies wiſe did anſwere make,</l>
                     <l>And ſhee her ſelfe affirmed to.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="29">
                     <head>Ver. 29.</head>
                     <l>Now of the ſpoile their parts they take,</l>
                     <l>And ſo they haue now much ado,</l>
                     <l>So many dameſels to divyde,</l>
                     <l>And colourd garments right well dy'de,</l>
                     <l>Right meete their ſhoulders all vnto.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="30">
                     <head>Verſe 30.</head>
                     <l>O LORD let all thoſe periſh ſo,</l>
                     <l>That enemies are to thee and thine:</l>
                     <l>And ſuch as loue thee moe and moe,</l>
                     <l>As cleare as ſunne aboue to ſhine;</l>
                     <l>As cleare as ſunne in his great ſtrength,</l>
                     <l>So that thy Church may at the length,</l>
                     <l>Sing foorth thy praiſes with mee and myne.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:25087:37"/>
               <head>The Song of CHANNAH. <hi>1.</hi> Samuel. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>Text.</head>
                  <p>MY heart rejoyceth in IEHOVAH, my horne is exalted in IEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH: my mouth is enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt my enemies for I rejoyce in thy ſalvation.</p>
                  <p>None holy like IEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH: for there is none but thou; and no rocke like to our GOD.</p>
                  <p>Multiplie not speaches highly, highly let not the old come out of your mouth: for IEHOVAH is a GOD of ſciences, and actions are not directed without him.</p>
                  <p>The bow of the ſtrong is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the weake is girded
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:25087:38"/>with strength.</p>
                  <p>They that were full of bread, hath hyred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and the hungrie hath ceaſed: while the barren hath borne ſeven: ſhee with many ſonnes is weakned.</p>
                  <p>IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH kils and giues life, casts downe to hell, and makes to aſcend.</p>
                  <p>IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH makes poore and rich, hee cauſes to fall, alſo hee exalts.</p>
                  <p>Hee raiſes the poore out of the duſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hee lifts vp the beggar from the dung hill; to make them ſit with prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and makes them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the throne of glorie, for to IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the earth doe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and he hath put vpon them the habitable world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:25087:38"/>Hee will preſerue the feete of his godly ones, and the wicked ſhall bee ſilent in darkneſſe: for a man ſhall not bee made ſtrong by his owne strength.</p>
                  <p>IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AH let their con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentions be trampled vnder foote: he ſhall thunder from Heaven vpon him: IEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH ſhall judge the ends of the earth: and ſhall giue strength to his King: and ſhall lift vp the horne of his CHRIST.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="paraphrase">
                  <pb facs="tcp:25087:37"/>
                  <head>Paraphraſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. OF this late, and great benefite O LORD which thou haſt beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon mee: I haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved ſo great joy: that my heart which before was heavie, now is light: and my weakeneſſe made ſtrong: my mouth cloſed before is now opned, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my enemies. Pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>inna &amp; others who reproached mee.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In thee O LORD I rejoyce juſtlie, who art moſt holy, hath no companion: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any ſo able to ſaue.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Speake not proudly, as thou was wont to doe, O my enemies: for the LORD knowes all things, and without him we can doe nothing.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 O Peninna thy ſtrength is gone, who inſulted vpon
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:25087:38"/>my barrenneſſe: and I who was weake am made ſtrong.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The caſe now is farre changed: thou was full of proſperitie: now thou muſt content thy ſelfe. I was in great affliction when I had no child: God hath now given to me one childe better nor ſeven, more worth then all thine</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The LORD is author of all changes, &amp; can bring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trares out of contrares, life out of death, proſperitie out of adverſitie, light out of darkneſſe. Gen. 1.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Povertie and riches are from the Lord: low eſtate and honor comes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. None ſo poore who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God if hee will can not make rich, none ſo vile but hee can make them honorable: even companions to prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: ſetting them in glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thrones: for the Lord hath ſet the pillars of the earth to it to ſtand vpon with the inhabitants there
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:25087:38"/>of, which pillar is his word and power.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. All the wayes of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hee will direct: and wicked men ſhall periſh in darkneſſe: for no man ſtandeth in his owne ſtrength.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. All who contend againſt GOD ſhall bee trode vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foote: hee ſhall thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from Heaven againſt everie one of them: the LORD ſhall judge the whole inhabitants of the world giving glory to his Sonne IESUS CHRIST the King of Kings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <head>The argument and analyſis of this ſong.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CHANNAH</hi> the wife of <hi>Elkanah</hi> (who alſo had another wife called <hi>Peninna</hi>) beeing a long time barren, which grieved her much: (for the Hebrew women knowing the promiſe of the ſeed of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to tread downe the head of the ſerpent, Gen. 3. and that that ſeed ſhould of the poſteritie of Abraham their father, eſteemed barrenneſſe a great croſſe) And her companion <hi>Peninna</hi> having children to Elkanah inſulting vpon her added affliction to the afflicted.</p>
                  <p>Therefore <hi>Channah</hi> prayed to God earneſtly to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her, to take away her reproach, and giue her a ſon:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:25087:39"/>The Lord heard her prayer, and gaue her a ſon, whom therefore ſhe called <hi>Samuell,</hi> that is to ſay: The ſtrong God heard: And ſhee beeing moved by the Spirit of GOD made and ſung this ſong. The parts of the ſong are 3. The 1: a propoſition with the reaſon thereof. verſe 1.2. The 2. a dehortation with the reaſons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, from the 3. verſe to the 9. The 3. the concluſion of the ſong. verſe 10.</p>
                  <p>The propoſition is of <hi>Channas</hi> joy in the LORD, ſet foorth by the motives of her joy. viz. the preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite recaued, and effect thereof, her abilitie to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere <hi>Peninna</hi> and all other that vpbraided her before. The reaſons of the propoſition are 2. the 1. taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the efficient joy, to wit: her deliverance from her griefe and reproach which ſhee aſcribs to GOD, and cals it, <hi>herſalvation.</hi> verſe 1. The 2. reaſon is taken from the vnchangeable nature of GOD, that hee is moſt holie, moſt ſtrong, moſt true. verſe 2. The dehortation is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned in the beginning of the 3. verſe. The ſumme of the propoſition is: That none, ſpecially <hi>Peninna,</hi> bee any more proude or vtter loftie language which is the effect of pryde: the reaſon of her dehortation are two, The 1. is taken from Gods omniſcience: The 2. from his powerfull providence. verſe 3. The 2. reaſon is il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrat by the effects thereof. 4.5.6.7.8. verſe. of which effects ſhee ſhoweth the cauſe in the end of the 8. verſe. The concluſion of the ſong containes a pophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the ſalvation of the godly, the deſtruction of the wicked: with a reaſon. 9. Next a petition conforme to the prophecie: with a repetition more cleare of the prophecie, verſe 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="annotations">
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:25087:39"/>
                  <head>Annotations vpon this ſong.</head>
                  <p>AS this ſong begins ſo it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinues full of metaphors purpoſes flowing from great feeling, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wanting conjunctions: In it alſo there be diverſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtrophees: of al theſe the judicious reader may make vſe.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 1. <hi>Thy ſalvation:</hi> ſo ſaid <hi>Simeon</hi> in his ſong Luk. 3. for the ſaincts of old by temporall benefites as this was to <hi>Channa,</hi> were ſtirred vp to thinke of the great ſalvation by CHRIST, which <hi>Simeon</hi> looked for, and ſaw more clearely and nearelie then his forbeares.</p>
                  <p>Verſ. 2. <hi>None holy, no rocke:</hi> This moſt true for holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and power are in GOD eſſentially and perfyte: in the creature by communication onely and in part, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compared with GOD. Iob. 4.18.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 5. <hi>Hath ceaſed:</hi> To wit, to bee hungrie and are filled.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seven:</hi> that is, many. Ruth. 4.11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Set out themſelf:</hi> to wit, for hyred ſervants for want of food.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 8. <hi>The pillars:</hi> See Iob. 48. v. 4. Pſal. 124. v. 8. Pſal. 112.26. and 104. verſe 5.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 10. <hi>To his KING:</hi> that is to ſay; to CHRIST IE SUS, to whom hee was to giue all power in Heaven and earth as his appointed King. Pſal. 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations of grounds for vſe and doctrine.</head>
                  <p>Obſ. 1. THis ſong is called a prayer becauſe it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to GOD, and in end hath a prayer: but
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:25087:40"/>the purpoſe of it is a thankſgiving: and ſo theſe well joyned according to the precept of the Apoſtle. Phi. 4.6.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 2. It is eaſie to GOD when hee will to make a heavie heart light and joyfull: a diſpyſed perſon honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: one ſilenced to ſpeake boldly. Theſe things and other benefites are obtained, by humiliation &amp; prayer.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 3. verſe 1. Whatſoever benefite GOD beſtows vpon vs, wee ſhould not ſo much thinke of it or vſe it, as looke to GOD the giver of it and praiſe him, not being as the ſwyoe, who feed vpon fallen fruit: but looke not vp to the tree.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 4. We ſhould labour to know Gods attributes by his word and workes, wee ſhould meditate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon: that wee may loue, feare, truſt him and obey his will alwayes.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 5. verſe 2. It is eaſier to tell what God is not. or to deny any creature to bee like him: then to tell what hee is, for God beeing alwayes infinit cannot be defyned affirmatiuelie ſo well as negatiuelie.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 6. Pryde is a hereditarie ſickneſſe in men and women: yet <hi>GOD reſiſteth the proude and giveth grace to the humble.</hi> Iam. 4.6.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 7. verſe 3. to the 8. The providence of GOD rules all things: maks all mutations among men Pſ. 107.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 8. Wee ſhould not look vpon things, and judge of them by preſent apperance: for the earth is as a ſtage: wee are players there vpon, everie one is not that hee ſeemeth to bee in the play: for a beggar there may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent a King: a wiſe man a foole: a wicked man a good: but wee ſhould abide patiently the cataſtrophe of the play, ſtaying till the morning, when everie man
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:25087:40"/>putteth on his owne coat: that is the morning of the reſurrection. Pſal. 49.14. 1. Iohn 3.1.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 9. verſe 9.10. The godly of old tooke their deliverances particular, and of the Kirk in generall, as types of their great ſalvation by Chriſt, which they looked for: 1. Pet. 1.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="song">
                  <head>This ſong paraphraſed in Engliſh meeter to the tune of the <hi>103.</hi> Pſalme.</head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>Verſe. 1.</head>
                     <l>MY heart rejoyceth in the Lord,</l>
                     <l>in him my horne is hie:</l>
                     <l>My mouth is open wyde and large</l>
                     <l>againſt my enemie.</l>
                     <l>In thy ſalvation I joye,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>none holy like to thee:</l>
                     <l>For there is none but thou, O Lord,</l>
                     <l>a God, a rocke to mee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <l>Speake thou no more words arrogant</l>
                     <l>as thou was wont before:</l>
                     <l>For God knowes all things very well,</l>
                     <l>and doth both leſſe and more.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <l>The ſtrong mans Bow is broken quyte,</l>
                     <l>the weake hath put on ſtrength:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>5.</head>
                     <l>The full beginne to begge their bread,</l>
                     <l>the hungrie eate at length.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="72" facs="tcp:25087:41"/>The barren hath her ſeven borne,</l>
                     <l>the mother of ſonnes is weake:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="6">
                     <head>6.</head>
                     <l>The Lord hee kills, and giveth life,</l>
                     <l>caſts downe and vp doth take:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="7">
                     <head>7.</head>
                     <l>Hee makes men poore: and hee makes rich,</l>
                     <l>hee humbles, and raiſeth hie</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="8">
                     <head>8.</head>
                     <l>Ev'n poore men from the dung and duſt,</l>
                     <l>Princes equalls to bee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For to the Lord the pillars of</l>
                     <l>the earth doe appertaine:</l>
                     <l>And therevpon hath hee ſet faſt</l>
                     <l>the world and all therein.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="9">
                     <head>9.</head>
                     <l>The feete hee will keepe of his Saints,</l>
                     <l>that they may never ſwerve:</l>
                     <l>The wicked ſhall in darkneſſe dwell,</l>
                     <l>as they do well deſerve.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No man ſhall by his owne ſtrength ſtand,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="10">
                     <head>10.</head>
                     <l>O Lord ſtoppe all their ſtrife:</l>
                     <l>The Lord will ſhoot his thunderbolts</l>
                     <l>at him from heaven right rife.</l>
                     <l>The ends of earth the Lord ſhal judge,</l>
                     <l>his King hee ſhall make ſtrong:</l>
                     <l>And hee ſhall his Anoynteds horne</l>
                     <l>lift vp ere it bee long.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:25087:41"/>
               <head>The Song of <hi>Hezechiah</hi> King of Iudah. Eſay. <hi>38.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>Text.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Said in the cutting of my dayes, I ſhall goe to the ports of the grave: I am deprived of the rest of my yeares.</p>
                  <p>I ſaid, I ſhall not ſee IAH, Iah in the land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving: I ſhall not behold man more, with the inhabitants of the world.</p>
                  <p>My habitation is gone and flitted from me, as a ſheep-heards tent: I haue cut off as a weaver my lyfe: he wil cut me off from the thrum: from the daye to the night thou will deſtroy mee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:25087:42"/>I reſolved vnto the morning as a Lyon hee ſo bruiſed all my bones, from the daye to the night thou conſumes me</p>
                  <p>As a crane, a ſwallow, I chettered: I ſighed like a dove; myne eyes were lifted vp to the hight: IEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH, I am weake give me rest.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall I ſaye? both hee ſaid to mee, and he himſelf hath done it: I ſhall goe on all my yeeres with the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of my ſoule.</p>
                  <p>Lord vpon theſe they ſhall live, in all wherein the lyfe of my spirit is, and thou wilt heale me and give me life.</p>
                  <p>Behold, for peace I had bit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terneſſe, and thou haſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved my ſoule from the pit of rottenneſſe: becauſe thou hast cast all my ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind thy back.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:25087:42"/>For the graue ſhal not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe vnto thee, death praiſe thee neither ſhall they hope who goe downe to the pit to thy trueth.</p>
                  <p>The living, the living hee ſhall confeſſe vnto thee: as I this day: the father to the ſonnes, ſhall make knowne thy trueth.</p>
                  <p>IEHOVAH to ſaue mee: Therefore my ſongs ſhall we play: all the dayes of our lyfe in the Houſe of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="paraphrase">
                  <pb facs="tcp:25087:41"/>
                  <head>Paraphraſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. VVHen I thought God was cutting the threed of my life, by deaths knife: I thought, and ſaid within my ſelfe: I ſhall now die young and child-leſſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Then my greateſt griefe was, that my bodily eyes ſhould not ſee God for a long time: and preſentlie to be deprived of the ſight of him, in the mirrour of his workes, word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. My dwelling place leaves mee, and I it: as a ſheep-herd leaveth his tent: the web of my life is cut out: as the weaver cutteth out a web out of his loome: for I made it ſhort by ſins God hath made it ſhort in his juſtice: and gives to mee no reſt daye or night.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:25087:42"/>4. After the nights vnreſt I looked for no better in the morning: but that hee cruelly wold deſtroy mee.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The cranes and ſwallows cannot ſpeak in their pain; yet they chatter, and the dove cheeps: ſo, vnder ſo great griefe and paine, I could doe nothing, but mourne, ſigh, lift vp my eyes and heart to God.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. It is the Lord, I can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay good nor euill: he hath ſpoken to mee by his ſervant Eſay, and is doing accordingly: I will never forget this heavie hand of God vpon mee.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Vpon ſuch meditations the godly ſhall be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: in time of ſickneſſe &amp; death: as I now, hoping yet for life and health, from thee O Lord.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 In place of peace &amp; health which I had, God layd v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me ſore ſickneſſe and trouble of Spirit: yet hee loves mee: becauſe, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit hee hath afflicted mee
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:25087:42"/>ſore: yet hath hee not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered mee to death. Pſal. 118. but hath forgiven my ſinnes, and ſet mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with peace.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. And this thou haſt done that yet I might worſhip thee in the land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, which bodies dead, and buried cannot doe.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. But man living as I am yet, ſhall praiſe thee: and one generation ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thy trueth, vnto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. The Lord was readie to ſaue mee. Therefore my ſong ſhall bee ſung, even this ſong tuned &amp; played, vpon muſicall inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, in witneſſe of mee and my peoples thankfulneſſe to God for this my delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <head>The argument and analyſis of this ſong.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HEzechiah</hi> king of Iudah beeing ſicke of a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat diſeaſe, which the learned thinke to haue bene a peſtilentious fever, becauſe mention is made of Byle. It was Gods will that the Prophet Eſay ſhould ſay to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:25087:43"/>him hee ſhould die be that diſeaſe: This meſſenger did much commoue Hezechiah: partly becauſe hee was then a younge man, and had no child: partly becauſe he beeing tormented both in body and ſpirit ſeared death: But chiefely becauſe hee having long before reſolved to ſerve God, and doe good to his Church, this good intention would faile. Being in this eſtate hee prayed, and weeped ſore, and the Lord heard and pittied him: Therfore he ſent againe to him the Prophet Eſay: with another more comportable commiſſion then the firſt: namely, that hee ſhould not die at this time: but haue fifteene yeares added to his yeares hee had lived alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: hee being thus comforted, beganne to recognoſce his thoughts in time of his ſickneſſe, and to conſider Gods great mercie toward him: for the which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to bee thankfull all the dayes of his life. Theſe things after hee had convaleſced hee put in write, and makes the argument of this ſong. The parts of the ſong are three: The 1. is a recognoſcing of his thoghts and words, in tyme of his ſickneſſe: from the 1. verſe to the 6. The 2. is the conſolation wherewith he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted himſelfe, from the 6. verſe to the 11. The 3. is the concluſion of the ſong verſe 11. As to the 1. part hee ſayeth his thoughts and words were theſe. 1. hee thought and ſaid hee would die of this diſeaſe. verſe 1. Next hee thought and ſaid hee would haue no more tyme place or occaſion to ſerue GOD among men li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving vpon the earth, verſe 2. Thirdly hee repeats his thoughts of death, in ſimilitude taken from ſheepe-heards, and weavers: verſe 3 4. Fourthly by the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of Crane, ſwallowes, doues: hee expreſſeth his
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:25087:43"/>paine &amp; prayer, verſe 5. As for the 2. part, to wit, his concluſion: the grounds thereof are theſe. 1. that GOD declared to him his will by the Prophet that he ſhould die: and it was GODS hand vpon him. 2. his reſolution to paſſe the reſt of his time in humilitie and repentance verſe 6. Thirdly, he comforts himfelf with Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, verſe 7. Fourthly, he comforteth himſelf with Gods mercie, ſet downe with the motive thereof, that God may bee honoured by his ſervants living vpon earth, verſe 8.9.10. The concluſion is, that hee wil praiſe God while he liveth, verſe 11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="annotations">
                  <head>Annotations vpon this Song.</head>
                  <p>Verſe 1. <hi>I ſaid:</hi> through impatience I thought with my ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I ſhall goe:</hi> a deſcription of death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſt of my yeares:</hi> which by the courſe of nature I might have looked for.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 2. <hi>I ſhall not ſee:</hi> I ſhall be deprived of Gods viſible preſence in his Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I AH, I AH:</hi> This doubling ſhoweth his great loue to God, and his worſhip.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 3. <hi>My habitation:</hi> hee compareth the life of man to a tent and webbe.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 4. <hi>I reſolved:</hi> That is, I layd my compt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Lyon:</hi> the like <hi>Iob, David, Chriſt</hi> felt.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 5. <hi>Chattered:</hi> being weake in body &amp; woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Spirit I could not vtter many words in prayer.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 6. <hi>What ſhall I ſay:</hi> to wit, to my Maker: ſee the like, chap. 39.8. Iob, 1.21. Heli, 1. Sam. 3.18, David, Pſal. 39 9 murmuring the contrare condemned.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 7. <hi>Theſe:</hi> he meaneth Gods word and works.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 8. <hi>For the grave:</hi> ſo David Pſal. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:25087:44"/>
                  <head>Obſervations of grounds for vſe and doctrine.</head>
                  <p>Obſ. 1. <hi>HEZECHIAH</hi> left behinde him this ſong as a monument of Gods mercie towards him: ſo did David many Pſalmes: and God honoured both with place in holy Scripture: which ſhall not bee forgot or loſt, ſo long as the world ſhall laſt: I will honour thoſe that honour mee, ſaith the LORD 1. Sam. 2.30.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 2. verſe. 1.2.3.4. Hee complaines not for feare of death; as loving this life ſo well, that hee had no knowledge, faith, or hope, of a better life after this: but heereby he ſhowes what paines he had in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, what agony in his ſouſe: beeing ſenſible of his ſins and of Gods anger: yet there betwo things that make men willing to die: ſome earthly thing whervnto their heart is teathered: or want of knowledge of the joyes of Heaven.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 3. verſ. 5. Hee could vtter few words in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for griefe and paine: yet God ſaw his teares, heard his pittifull ſighs and groanes: This ſhould teach vs in greateſt troubles, yea in the midſt of the ſhaddow of death to hold faſt our confidence in God. Pſ. 23.4. Heb. 10.35.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 4. verſ. 6. The grounds that Hezeckiah laid for his comfort, wee ſhould vſe to the lyke end: ſee the analyſis.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 5. <hi>The LORD wounds and heales againe; kils &amp; giues life:</hi> therefore wee ſhould alwayes feare, ſerue, and truſt in him. 1. Sam. 2.6.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 6. The chiefe end of mans lyfe is to know God and ſerue him: therefore this ſhould bee the principall
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:25087:44"/>cauſe of our deſire to liue.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 7. Death is a web of our owne ſpinning: becauſe by ſinne wee brought it on vs; yet God is ſaid to cut out the web of our life: becauſe he begins it, promoves it, ends it when hee pleaſes. This may bee the morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Poets fable of the three weirdſiſters.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 8. When God forgiueth a man his ſinne hee takes away the puniſhment alſo, as Hezechiah teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by his experience: and this refuteth the doctrine of Romaniſts: of remisſion of ſinne: and reſervation of puniſhment where vpon they build purgatorie.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 9.7.8 9.10.11. verſe. When God hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted vs and delivered vs againe, we ſhould be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, thankfull, penitent, praying for perſeverence leaſt wee fall againe with Hezechiah. Eſ. 3.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="song">
                  <head>This ſong paraphraſed in Engliſh meeter to the tune of the <hi>102.</hi> Pſalme.</head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>Verſe. 1.</head>
                     <l>WHen that I thought my dayes were cut,</l>
                     <l>I ſaid, vnto the graue I'me put,</l>
                     <l>My yeares are ſpent no moe remaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>GOD in this life to ſee againe,</l>
                     <l>No longer men I ſay behold,</l>
                     <l>Heere vpon earth although I would.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <l>My tabernacle now is rent,</l>
                     <l>I flit as ſheepheards doe from tent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My web like weaver I cut out,</l>
                     <l>My like I meane: for thou but doubt,</l>
                     <l>Will mee cut off O LORD with noy,</l>
                     <l>And mee from day to night deſtroy,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="80" facs="tcp:25087:45"/>No reſt I get into the night.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <l>And in the morning by his might,</l>
                     <l>Lyke to a lyon hee mee breakes,</l>
                     <l>Both day and night ſo ſore hee ſhakes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>5.</head>
                     <l>As Crane or Swallow, or lyke Doue,</l>
                     <l>I murne, I ſigh, I chatter now:</l>
                     <l>I lift my eyes, I ſay this beſt,</l>
                     <l>LORD I am weake, giue thou mee reſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="6">
                     <head>6.</head>
                     <l>I hold my peace becauſe that hee,</l>
                     <l>Both ſaid and did all this to mee:</l>
                     <l>With ſorrow humble will I goe,</l>
                     <l>Spending my life heereafter ſo.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="7">
                     <head>7.</head>
                     <l>Vpon thy promiſe wee depend,</l>
                     <l>And on thy mercie without end:</l>
                     <l>Theſe are the life of this my ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>To make mee heale thou thinks it meete.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="8">
                     <head>8.</head>
                     <l>In place of peace I had great paine,</l>
                     <l>Thou lov'd my ſoule brought it againe</l>
                     <l>From pit: for all my ſinnes paſt,</l>
                     <l>Behind thy backe now thou haſt caſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="9">
                     <head>9.</head>
                     <l>Man gone to graue, cannot confeſſe,</l>
                     <l>Nor praiſe thy name, there more or leſſe,</l>
                     <l>Nor can they truſt more in thy treuth:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="10">
                     <head>10</head>
                     <l>But ſuch on earth, whom thou haſt reuth;</l>
                     <l>As I this day now living doe,</l>
                     <l>Thy trueth their ſeed will tell vnto.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="11">
                     <head>11.</head>
                     <l>The LORD was readie mee to ſaue,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:25087:45"/>
               <head>The ſong of the bleſſed Virgin Marie. Luk. chap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="text">
                  <p>MY ſoule magnifieth the LORD.</p>
                  <p>And my spirit leaps for joy: in GOD my Saviour.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe hee hath looked vnto the humilitie of his hand-maid: for behold from this time, all nations ſhall call mee bleſſed.</p>
                  <p>For hee who is mighty hath done vnto me great things: and holy is his Name.</p>
                  <p>And his mercie to generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of generations, to them that feare him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:25087:46"/>Hee hath done a powerfull worke: with his arme hee hath ſcattered the proude with the diſcourſe of their heart.</p>
                  <p>Hee hath pulled the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie out of thrones: and hath exalted the humble.</p>
                  <p>Hee filled the hungry with good things, and hath ſent the rich away emptie.</p>
                  <p>Hee hath taken vp Iſrael his child to remember his mercie.</p>
                  <p>As hee spake to our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Abraham and his ſeed for ever.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="paraphrase">
                  <pb facs="tcp:25087:45"/>
                  <p n="1">1. I Am ſo raviſhed with admiration of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, goodneſſe, and power of GOD toward mee: that all the powers of my ſoule concurre with my tounge to praiſe him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And this is the cauſe of the exceeding great joy of my ſpirit: even to thinke vpon GOD my Saviour.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Who hath looked vpon mee his handmaid of low degree: and hath honored me ſo: that now in al tims to come all people ſhall proclaime mee a bleſſed woman, the mother of that bleſſed ſeed.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 For the ſtrong and holie GOD hath done great and wonderfull things by me.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. And he is not onely good to me, but alſo to all that loue him and ſerue him in all ages.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:25087:46"/>6. By his mightie power he hath wroght a great work he hath diſſipat the proud, and all their devyces.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. God reſiſteth the proud: and giveth grace to the humble: exalting them which will be ſeene ſhort<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly vpon my Sonne &amp; me: and Herod.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Such as were poore and in hard eſtate: as my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and I, he hath made aboundantly content: And vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rich men as Herod he is bringing great miſerie and male-contentment.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. With his owne hand hee hath lifted vp Iſrael his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant: and exalted him: who before was deſpiſed, remembring his covenant of grace, made with Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Iſaac and Iacob our fathers.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 Even that everlaſting co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant concerning the ſeed of Abraham.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <head>The argument and analyſis of this ſong.</head>
                  <p>MARIE having harkned to the meſſage of the Angell <hi>Gabriel:</hi> haſted to <hi>Hebron</hi> a towne of the trybe of Iudah, pertaining to the Levits, ſituat among
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:25087:46"/>the mountaines: where Zachariah &amp; Eliſabeth her coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin dwelt: to ſhow her this mervelous worke of God with her, that ſhe a virgin not knowing man had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the holy Ghoſt: that child who ſhould bee the Meſſias promiſed to the fathers: Now ſo ſoone as Mary came to Eliſabeth, and ſaluted her: At the voyce of Maries ſalutation: Iohn the Baptiſt who was to bee the forerunner of CHRIST, leapt within the wombe of Eliſabeth: And Eliſabeth beeing filled with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, told Marie the tydings, ſhe came to tell her: before Marie vttered a word more then the ſalutation: and ſhee proclaimed Marie to bee a bleſſed woman, the mother of her LORD, &amp; the fruite of her wombe bleſſed; and ſhew her that ſo ſoone as ſhee heard the voyce of her ſalutation: her owne child leapt for joy within her bellie. Even Iohn (ſayeth <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, ſaluteth Chriſt, whom as yet hee could, not ſalute with words. And Eliſabeth aſſured Marie, that that ſhould come to paſſe, which was told her from the Lord by his Angell: Then Marie moved by the holie Spirit vttered the words of this ſong containing the praiſe of GOD: for his great mercie and goodneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her: and towards all his ſervants in all ages: and for his wiſe, juſt, powerfull providence, for his Church and againſt the enemies thereof: according to his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with Abraham and his ſeed for ever.</p>
                  <p>The parts of the ſong are 2. the 1. containeth a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of her praiſing of GOD and rejoycing in him. verſe 1.2. The 2. containeth reaſons of the propoſition: which are 7. in number. The 1. is taken from GODS goodneſſe towards her and the conſequent thereof, that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:25087:47"/>hence foorth all ages ſhall call her bleſſed, verſe 3. The 2 is taken from GODS wonderfull power, in working with her, and his holineſſe. verſe 4. The 3. is taken from the continuing of Gods mercie to his ſervants &amp; their poſteritie. verſe 5. The 4. is taken from Gods power over the enemies of his Church. verſe 6. The 5. is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from GODS power and juſtice over wicked men bee they never ſo mightie: and his power, goodneſſe, &amp; grace to ſuch as in humilitie ſerue him. verſe 7. The 6. is taken from Gods compaſſion vpon poore ones: &amp; his diſpyſing of the rich, who truſt in their riches. The 7. is taken from Gods goodneſſe to his people Iſraell and the efficient cauſe thereof, to wit, his covenant with their fathers. verſe 9.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="annotations">
                  <head>Annotations vpon this Song.</head>
                  <p>Verſe 1. <hi>MAgnifieth:</hi> that is, inlarges it ſelf to think of his greatneſſe and goodneſſe: for no creature can comprehend GOD fully, farre leſſe adde to his perfection.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 2. <hi>In:</hi> or for: and this ſheweth the efficient cauſe and verie object of her joy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Saviour:</hi> The Syriak interpretation is, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning mee.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 3. <hi>Looked:</hi> that is, favourablie accepted: Gen. 4. chap. v. 4.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Humilitie:</hi> The word imports a low and deſpyſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: &amp; not the merite of vertue in her: as they alledge who mantaine that divine worſhip is due to Marie in a hy degree: But <hi>Theophylactus</hi> exponing theſe words ſayeth better: I ſhall bee called bleſſed not for my ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:25087:47"/>but becauſe GOD hath done great things for me.</p>
                  <p>Verſe. 5. <hi>To generations:</hi> according to the promiſe Exod. 20.6. Pſal. 103.17.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Feare him:</hi> feare in holy Scripture oft ſignifyeth all duety wee owe to GOD: and is to bee vnderſtood of the filial not ſervile feare. Rom. 5.15.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 6. <hi>A powerfull thing:</hi> the Syriak interprets this, victorie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Scattered:</hi> as the whirle winde doth chaffe. Pſal. 1.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 8. <hi>Hungrie:</hi> ſhe alluds to the words of Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na in her ſong.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Taken vp:</hi> with his hand to deliver: which the Greeke word properly ſignifieth, as <hi>Galen</hi> witneſſes, and ſo is to bee exponed Heb. 3.16. and the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration heereof giveth another meaning to that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, then commonly interpreters doe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Child:</hi> Syriak his ſervant, as Eſay. 41, 8.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations of grounds for vſe and doctrine.</head>
                  <p>Obſ. 1. THis the firſt ſong in the new Teſtament ſung by the bleſſed Virgin Marie: as the firſt ſong in the old Teſtament was ſung by Marie Moſes ſiſter, both about one time of the yeare, both by women, both by Maries: and in many things the purpoſes of both agrees.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 2. verſe. I. 2. The ſpirit of GOD in lightneth the eyes of the minds of his ſervants to ſee clearely his benefites, and their greatneſſe: he fils their hearts with ſpirituall joy: &amp; opens their mouth to praiſe: while as the wicked are like to ſwyne who eat fruit falling from
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:25087:48"/>the tree: but never looke where from it came.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 3. verſ. 3. God is ſaid in holy Scripture to reſpect or looke vpon men or women when he ſhowes any token of his favour to them: and by the contrare not to reſpect or looke vpon them, when hee is angry: &amp; the ſimilitude is borrowed from parents or maſters to their children or ſervants.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 4 Marie heere &amp; in the verſes following ſeemes to allude to the 98. Pſalme, teaching vs to bee well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint with holy Scripture, that wee may make vſe thereof in due time.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 5. verſ. 4. 5. Gods promiſes to the godly, import everlaſting good things: And therefore the per formance of his promiſe by temporall benefites, ſhould bee to vs pledges of his eternall loue.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 6. Compare the verſes following with Pſal. 1. Pſal. 63. Eſay 29.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 7. GOD takes the wicked in their owne crafts, making evill counſell worſe to the giuer.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 8. When God will put forth his hand to helpe, he comforts his Church, confounds his enemies Eſ. 41.10</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 9. verſe 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. God is faithfull and fails not his ſervants. Ioſ. 1.5. Heb. 13.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="song">
                  <head>This ſong paraphraſed in Engliſh meeter to the tune of the <hi>19.</hi> Pſalme.</head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>Verſe. 1.</head>
                     <l>MY ſoule the Lord doth magnifie,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>and ſprit in him rejoyce:</l>
                     <l>Hee is my GOD and Saviour,</l>
                     <l>To him I ſing with noyſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:25087:48"/>
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <l>For hee the poore eſtate of mee,</l>
                     <l>his hand-maid did reſpect:</l>
                     <l>And now from hence no people ſhall,</l>
                     <l>to call mee bleſt neglect.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <l>The mightie LORD to mee hath done,</l>
                     <l>things marvelous and great.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>5.</head>
                     <l>His Name is holy and his grace,</l>
                     <l>ſits in eternall ſeate.</l>
                     <l>To ſuch as feare his holy Name,</l>
                     <l>and worſhip him in treuth:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="6">
                     <head>6.</head>
                     <l>A mightie worke his arme hath wrought,</l>
                     <l>the Proude deſtroy'd but reuth.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="7">
                     <head>7.</head>
                     <l>The mightie men out of their thrones,</l>
                     <l>hee pulled hath with ſtrength:</l>
                     <l>And ſuch as were of low degree,</l>
                     <l>exalted at the length.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="8">
                     <head>8.</head>
                     <l>With good things hee the hungrie fils,</l>
                     <l>the rich ſends poore away.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="9">
                     <head>9,</head>
                     <l>His ſervant Iſrael hath hee tane,</l>
                     <l>for to protect alway.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For why, hee hath remembered,</l>
                     <l>his covenant of grace.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="10">
                     <head>10.</head>
                     <l>Which with our fathers hee did make.</l>
                     <l>and ſeed to come in place:</l>
                     <l>Of Abraham I chiefely meane,</l>
                     <l>and his poſteritie,</l>
                     <l>That they ſhould finde to them and theirs,</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:25087:49"/>
               <head>The Song of ZACHARIE. Luke. <hi>1.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>Text.</head>
                  <p>BLeſſed be the LORD the God of Iſraell: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee hath viſited and made redemption to his people.</p>
                  <p>And hath raiſed vp the horne of ſalvation to vs in the houſe of David his child.</p>
                  <p>As he spake by the mouth of his holy Prophets: which haue beene ſince the world beganne.</p>
                  <p>Salvation from our enemies &amp; from the hand of al that hate vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:25087:49"/>To make mercie with our fathers, and to remember his holy teſtament.</p>
                  <p>The oath which he ſwore to Abraham our father.</p>
                  <p>To giue vnto vs delivered from the hand of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to ſerue him without feare.</p>
                  <p>In holyneſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe before him; all the dayes of our lyfe.</p>
                  <p>And thou, babe; ſhall bee called the Prophet of the most High, for thou ſhall goe before: before the face of the LORD to prepare his wayes.</p>
                  <p>To giue the knowledge of ſalvation to his people, in the remiſſion of their ſinnes</p>
                  <p>By the bowels of mercie of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:25087:50"/>our GOD, by the which he hath viſited vs who comes from aboue.</p>
                  <p>To ſhine to them that ſit in darkneſſe &amp; in the ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death, to direct our feete in the way of peace.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="paraphrase">
                  <pb facs="tcp:25087:49"/>
                  <head>Paraphraſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Let God bee praiſed and preached moſt worthie of praiſe: becauſe that now hee hath declared, that he was mindefull of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in ſending his Sonne to viſit and redeeme them</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And now while as the ſtrength of Iſrael ſeemed to bee gone, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made to David to haue failed: he hath raiſed vp his CHRIST: who by his ſtrength ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw our enemies: and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh the kingdome in the houſe of David.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. According to his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by his ſervants: conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in all ages ſince the beginning.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Who prophecied that we ſhould bee delivered from our enemies and from the power of all who hate vs.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:25087:49"/>5. And to performe his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie promiſed. to our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: and ſhew hee did remember his covenant made, ſeald to Abraham.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. By oath, viſion, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. That wee beeing delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the power of our enemies, might ſerue him willingly &amp; boldly.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. In holyneſſe and true righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſneſſe in his ſight con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually (who ſearches the hearts and raines) ſo long as wee liue.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. But now thou my younge ſonne: though thou ſeeme litle worth: yet thou ſhall be a great one: even furri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the great King: and his forerunner to prepare his peoples hearts to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue him.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Opning to them the way of ſalvation, in repentance and faith in the blood of Chriſt the Lambe of God who takes away the ſins of the world.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Which is the greateſt
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:25087:50"/>mercie given vs by GOD: manifeſting his Sonne in the fleſh: who commeth from Heaven.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Who alſo ſhall be a light to the Gentiles, who now ſit in darkneſſe and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorance: &amp; lead both vs and them to true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <head>The argument and analyſis of this ſong.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ZACHARIE</hi> the father of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, a prieſt of the order of <hi>Abiah:</hi> when hee was doing his office according to the order of his courſe, in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the LORD. <hi>Gabriel</hi> the Angell appeared vnto him and told him that his wife Eliſabeth ſhould beare him a ſonne: &amp; commanded him to call his name <hi>Iohn:</hi> Alſo hee ſhew him that hee ſhould bee that <hi>Elias</hi> of whom <hi>Malachi</hi> prophecied chap 4. v. 5. Which meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage Zacharie doubted of: conſidering that both hee and Eliſabeth were old: and ſhe had beene all her dayes till then barren. Therefore he was ſtriken with dumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vntill the day Iohn was borne: ſo that vpon the eight day after, when they were about the circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the child, they ſpeared at him how the childe ſhould be called: &amp; he asking writting tables, becauſe he could not ſpeake, wrote, his name ſhall bee IOHN: and immediatly his tongue was looſed: and he opned his mouth, and praiſed GOD. And beeing filled with
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:25087:50"/>the Spirit of GOD hee ſpake the words of this ſong: The ſumme of it is: he praiſed GOD for performing of his promiſe concerning Meſſiah: made to their father Abraham and to David, and foretold by the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſince the world beganne: and in the end he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecieth that his ſonne Iohn ſhould be the forerunner and furriour of CHRIST.</p>
                  <p>The parts of the ſong are three; The 1. containeth the praiſe of GOD or an exhortation to praiſe him ver. 1. at the beginning: The 2. part containes the reaſons of the exhortation: from the 1. to the 9. And they are in number 3. The 1. is the viſitation of his people. The 2. is the redemption of them: verſe 1. The 3. reaſon is the raiſing vp of the horne of ſalvation in the houſe of David. verſe 2. All theſe 3. reaſons are illuſtrate, by comparing the promiſes of God and prophecies with theſe things, the event and accompliſhment of them verſe 3.4.5.6.7.8. The 3. part of the ſong, containes a prophecie concerning his ſonne Iohn: that he ſhould bee called a Prophet, be the furriour and ſorerunner of CHRIST. verſe 9. Next the miniſtrie and doctriné of Iohn, viz. to point out Meſſiah: prepare the people to receaue him: teach the doctrine of repentance &amp; faith, for receaving by the mercie of GOD remiſſion of ſinnes verſe 10.11. Thirdly hee ſets downe the finall cauſe of CHRISTS firſt comming, to wit, to giue light, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, life eternall to all thoſe that ſhould beleeue in him verſe 12.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="annotations">
                  <head>Annotations vpon this ſong.</head>
                  <p>Verſe 1. <hi>BLeſſed:</hi> The verb, be, is to be vnderſtood <hi>Viſited:</hi> This word in holy Scripture
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:25087:51"/>ſignifieth, whiles to puniſh, Exod. 20. whiles to doe good, as heere, where it imports the perſonall preſence of GOD in his Sonne IESUS CHRIST comming in the fleſh, to ſee the eſtate of GODS Church on earth: and to redeeme them. See Exod. 3.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Redemption:</hi> This word is diverſly taken. 1. for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering by force and power out of the hand of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, as GOD redeemed his people out of Egypt. 2. For going free with the enemies good will: as the redemption from the Babylonian Captivitie. 3. For ranſoming, that is, paying the juſt pryce, as heere and els where.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 2 <hi>The Horne:</hi> That is, the ſtrength, a metaphor from horned beaſts.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 7. <hi>Without feare:</hi> That is, with confidence: Eph. 3.12. for feare heere doth not ſignifie religious reverence, but griefe for evill to come.</p>
                  <p>Verſe. 10. <hi>In the remiſſion:</hi> or by the remiſſion of ſinnes, which is the manner by the which GOD ſaves vs. Rom. 4.7.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 11. <hi>Who commeth from aboue:</hi> The Greeke word properly ſignifieth the ſunne ryſing: And Meſſiah is ſo called in Hebrew. Ier. 23.5. Zach. 3.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Peace:</hi> In the old Teſtament often ſignifieth proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and in the New: but heere it imports happineſſe everlaſting: In this way CHRIST by his word leads vs: for hee is the way, the veritie and life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations of grounds for vſe and doctrine.</head>
                  <p>Obſ. 1 ALbeit theſe words of <hi>Zacharie</hi> bee called a prophecie: yet the learned calleth this the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:25087:51"/>ſecond ſong in the New Teſtament: There is indeed a prophecie in the foure laſt verſes: but the former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainerh the praiſe of GOD.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 2. verſe 1. It hath alwayes beene the practiſe of the godly after ſight or ſenſe of Gods benefites tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall or ſpirituall, to praiſe GOD: ſo ſhould wee.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 3. GOD maketh his promiſes to his Church good, when there is leaſt appearance: hence the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb: when man is weakeſt GOD is ſtrongeſt.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 4. verſe 2. The raiſing vp of the horne of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the houſe of David, is the continuing of Davids kingdome, to bee an everlaſting kingdome in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of CHRIST.</p>
                  <p>Obſ 5. The compariſon of prophecies with their event argue the Scripture to be the word of GOD.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 6 verſe 3. All the Patriarchs and Prophets be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued and looked for the comming of Chriſt. 1. Pet. 1.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 7. verſe 4 5.6. The Covenant of grace is: that God would forgiue vs our ſinnes: ſave vs from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, chiefely ſpirituall, ſinne, Satan, death, put vs in the eſtate of grace, and bring vs to glorie: which bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites Chriſt meriteth to vs by his death.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 8. verſe 8. The end of our redemption is, that wee ſerue God &amp; Chriſt his Sonne in true holineſſe &amp; righteouſnes before him: beware of hypocriſie, Pſ. 50.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 9. Iohn new borne is inſtalled in his office by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 10. verſe 10. The onely way to ſalvation by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misſion of ſinnes through the merit of the blood of Chriſt, was ſhewed in the bloody ſacrifices from the beginning, types heereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:25087:52"/>Obſ. 11. Gods mercie is over all his workes. Pſal. 145.9. but the bowels of his mercie, that is, his ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aboundant love towards his choſen in redeeming of them by Chriſt his Sonne.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 12. verſe 11. CHRIST is compared to the morning ſtarre, the ſunne, the light, an orient from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue: all which haue good vſe to comfort vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="song">
                  <head>This ſong paraphraſed in Engliſh meeter to the tune of the <hi>18.</hi> Pſalme.</head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>1.</head>
                     <l>THE LORD, the GOD of Iſrael,</l>
                     <l>bee bleſt and praiſde alway:</l>
                     <l>For hee with great redemption,</l>
                     <l>hath viſit vs this day.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>The horne now of ſalvation,</l>
                     <l>to vs is raiſed hie,</l>
                     <l>Vnto the houſe of David, his</l>
                     <l>beloved: as wee ſee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <l>As did foretell our fathers all,</l>
                     <l>who prophets were by name:</l>
                     <l>Since that the world did firſt beginne,</l>
                     <l>by them hee ſpoke the ſame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <l>That wee ſhould bee delivered,</l>
                     <l>out of our enemies hand:</l>
                     <l>From everie one that did vs hate,</l>
                     <l>or that ſhould vs withſtand:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>5.</head>
                     <l>According to the Covenant,</l>
                     <l>once with our fathers made</l>
                     <l>Of mercie, now remembered,</l>
                     <l>though they long ſince bee deade.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="6">
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:25087:52"/>
                     <head>6.</head>
                     <l>The oath which vnto Abraham,</l>
                     <l>our father hee did ſweare:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="7">
                     <head>7,</head>
                     <l>To give to vs deliverance,</l>
                     <l>to ſerue him without feare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="8">
                     <head>8.</head>
                     <l>In righteouſneſſe and holyneſſe,</l>
                     <l>ſincere before his face:</l>
                     <l>So long as life ſhould in vs dure,</l>
                     <l>and that from race to race.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="9">
                     <head>9.</head>
                     <l>And thou my little babe ſhall bee,</l>
                     <l>prophet of the moſt Hie,</l>
                     <l>And ſo bee cald, becauſe that thou,</l>
                     <l>the LORD himſelfe ſhall ſee.</l>
                     <l>And thou before him firſt ſhall goe,</l>
                     <l>his way for to prepare:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="10">
                     <head>10.</head>
                     <l>Inſtructing to ſalvation,</l>
                     <l>his people leſſe and maire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="11">
                     <head>11.</head>
                     <l>That vnto them remiſſion,</l>
                     <l>of all their ſinnes is given.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="12">
                     <head>12.</head>
                     <l>By GODS moſt tender mercie now,</l>
                     <l>ſet foorth before our eyne:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For now the Sunne of righteouſneſſe,</l>
                     <l>hath ſhyned from aboue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="13">
                     <head>13.</head>
                     <l>To them that ſit in darkneſſe, and</l>
                     <l>in ſhaddow of the graue.</l>
                     <l>Our paths for to direct into,</l>
                     <l>the way that leads to peace:</l>
                     <l>And everlaſting glorie next,</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:25087:53"/>
               <head>The Song of the Angels at the birth of <hi>CHRIST.</hi> Luk. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>Text.</head>
                  <p>GLORY to GOD in the moſt High: and in the earth peace: to men good will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="paraphrase">
                  <head>Paraphraſe.</head>
                  <p>GLORY is giving to GOD in the moſt hy Heavens: peace is now vpon earth: and good news to men.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <head>The argument and analyſis of this ſong.</head>
                  <p>ONE Angell maketh manifeſt the birth of Chriſt, to ſhepheards watching their flocks in the night: &amp; there appeared to them with the Angell a multitude of heavenly ſouldiers, that is to ſay: other Angels: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulating, the nativitie of Chriſt, and ſinging this ſong: The parts of it are 3. The 1. concerneth God, that the Angels in HEAVEN were praiſing him for manifeſting his Sonne in the fleſh. The 2. concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth mankynd vpon earth to whom peace is wiſhed. The 3. maketh mention of a greater benefite to them, even GODS loving kindneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="annotations">
                  <head>Annotations vpon this ſong.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GOod will:</hi> The Syriak exponeth a good meſſage: <hi>Peace:</hi> For ſo it was then through all the world: <hi>Men:</hi> The Syriak exponeth the ſonnes of man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations for vſe and doctrine.</head>
                  <p>IT is cuſtomable to earthly Princes to congratulate by their Ambaſſadors one another, when children
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:25087:53"/>are procreated to them: but the lyke of this was never heard before nor ſhall be heereafter: That the eternall, infinite, everlaſting GOD, ſhould ſend from Heaven a multitude of Angels, his Ambaſſadours to congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the birth of a bairne: teaching vs in what eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion GOD hath his ſonne new manifeſted in the fleſh: how willing hee ſent him in the world to redeeme vs.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 2. Outward peace is little worth where peace of conſcience is away, therefore to peace is well joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Gods good will: the ſenſe whereof giveth peace inward.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="song">
                  <head>This ſong paraphraſed in Engliſh meeter to the tune of the <hi>117.</hi> Pſalme.</head>
                  <l>IN higheſt Heaven to GOD is glore,</l>
                  <l>Let men on earth yet praiſe him more:</l>
                  <l>For hee to vs his peace hath ſend,</l>
                  <l>In praiſing him our life to ſpend:</l>
                  <l>To men hath ſhew'd his great good will,</l>
                  <l>To laud his name ſhould wee be ſtill?</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſong of <hi>Simeon,</hi> Luke. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>Text.</head>
                  <p>NOW LORD thou let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test goe thy ſervant in peace, according to thy word,</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:25087:54"/>For my eyes haue ſeene thy ſalvation.</p>
                  <p>Which thou hast prepared before the face of all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
                  <p>A light to the revelation of the Gentiles, and the glorie of thy people Iſraell.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="paraphrase">
                  <head>Paraphraſe</head>
                  <p n="1">1. LORD thou ſaid I ſhould not depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this life vntill I had ſeene Meſſias: now I haue ſeene him: and am readie to die
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:25087:54"/>with peace and joy.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Even with the eyes of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, I haue ſeene him, who ſhall ſaue vs.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Even Chriſt Ieſus vpon whom both Iews &amp; Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſhould looke: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue in him their ſaviour.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That light that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to bee revealed to the Gentiles: and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Iews, being fleſh of their fleſh, and bone of their bones.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <head>The argument and analyſis of this ſong.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SIMEON</hi> a juſt and godly man, living in the dayes when IESUS CHRIST was borne: had a revelation from the holy Ghoſt, that hee ſhould not ſee death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, with his bodilie eyes hee had ſeene the LORDS CHRIST, And when <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> brought Ieſus to Ieruſalem, to preſent him to the LORD, and offer according to the law of purification of women. <hi>Simeon</hi> beeing mooved by the Spirit of GOD; came to the Temple and tooke the babe IESUS in his armes: and bleſſed GOD, and vttered the words of this ſong: ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therewithall what child this was, and what hee ſhould bee. The parts of the ſong are 2. The 1. in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance a thankſgiving: in forme an affirmatiue propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: containing beſide the ſubject and attribute: the circumſtance of time in the word, <hi>now:</hi> and of manner
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:25087:54"/>in the words, <hi>according to thy word:</hi> verſe 1. The 2 part is a reaſon of the thankſgiving or propoſition: becauſe he had ſeene with his bodilie eyes the Meſſiah, whom he deſcribs, calling him the <hi>Gentils light, Iſraels glory.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="annotations">
                  <head>Annotations vpon this ſong.</head>
                  <p>Verſ. 1. <hi>LEttest goe:</hi> The Greeke word is a meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor from ſhips lowſing from one place to another port, the Syriak hath: Now let mee goe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In peace:</hi> That is, happilie, with inward peace &amp; joy Verſe 2. <hi>My eyes:</hi> that is, the eyes of my body; for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwayes Abraham long before Simeon ſaw Chriſt with the eye of ſaith Iohn 8. &amp; is that ſight which the Prophets deſired to ſee, beſide the ſight of faith. 1. Pet 1</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſalvation:</hi> That is, IESUS the Saviour, thy Son: The Syriak hath, thy gratious.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 3. <hi>Before the face:</hi> as a worke to looke vnto, and a light to follow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Glory:</hi> becauſe, come of them according to the fleſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations for vſe and doctrine.</head>
                  <p>Obſ. 1. <hi>SImeon</hi> Swan-lyke for whyte haires, ſang this ſweet ſong before his death: As Moſes did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Deut. 32.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 2. The dayes were verie evill wherein <hi>Simeon</hi> lived, which did appearantly make him wearie of his lyfe: So <hi>Elias, Ieremiah,</hi> and other holy men haue bene tempted with this tentation.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 3. The metaphor fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mariners hauing a cable caſt faſt where they minde not to ſtay, and caſting it lowſe when they will goe home: teacheth vs that the life of the godly is a voyage throgh many ſtormes: their death
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:25087:55"/>a go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> home to their. Heaven their port, their reſt.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 4. The houre of our death is appointed by God: therefore wee ſhould neither too much loue life not haſten or feare to die.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 5. verſ. 1. The end of the godly is peace Pſ. 37. Eſ. 57. but no peace to the wicked, ibid.</p>
                  <p>Obſ. 6. verſ. 3. Chriſt is ſet forth by the preaching of the Ghoſpell before all people: yet ſome looke vpon him and offend: others looke vpon him and belieue. 1. Cor. 1.13. 1. Pet. 2.8, 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="song">
                  <head>This ſong in meeter: to the tune of the <hi>25.</hi> Pſ.</head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>1.</head>
                     <l>NOW letteſt thou, O LORD,</l>
                     <l>thy ſervant part in peace:</l>
                     <l>According to thy promiſe made,</l>
                     <l>to mee of thy good grace:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>For why? my eyes haue ſeene,</l>
                     <l>my LORD and Saviour.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <l>Whom thou haſt ſet before our face,</l>
                     <l>to looke on every houre:</l>
                     <l>And als before the face,</l>
                     <l>of other people all:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <l>For heer's the light revealed now,</l>
                     <l>to Gentiles whom wee call,</l>
                     <l>In whom Iſra'l may glore,</l>
                     <l>as beeing Abrahams feed.</l>
                     <l>And ſent to them now in due time,</l>
                     <l>in time of their great need.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25087:55"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
